Chapter 1: Social Gatherings

Author's Note 4/28/16- This fiction is divisive, with many people hating it. If you read for the destination and not the journey you will not like this. At all. This story started as a bunch of vignettes and grew into something more, but at its heart it remains a connected group of stories. There are large arcs, but they do not all resolve cleanly. - Tao

Draco looked across the table at his mother, His Mother, and quietly sipped another spoon of Diricawl soup. Narcissa stared at her glass of wine, untouched in an ornate silver goblet engraved with three snakes poking their heads over the edge of the lip, as if drinking. The candles on the table burnt low, but had never (in all the years Draco had known) managed to finish that final inch of wax.

The chair at the head of the table sat empty.

"I'm sorry, my son. I don't know how to act. I remember you as a baby. And to find a decade gone? Lucius gone? Our house …. " Draco put down his spoon, his mind racing with lessons, but … lessons were not for family.

"Mother. I don't know, either." Draco pushed his chair back and the house elves immediately scurried in, heads down, and cleared the table. "I don't remember you." He saw her try to hide a pained look and grimaced "No, I mean, I have glimpses in my mind" that Harry said are just me remembering a daydream, not a real memory. He paused while the elves left, as noiselessly as they'd entered. "But, you … you were coo-ing at me. And I don't remember you being gone, your Death, I remember Father telling me the stories over and over. I was supposed to love you automatically, by being your child, and that has been taking away from us. But I do remember the coo-ing."

Narcissa smiled at that and finally picked up the glass of wine. "That could have been anyone. All the witches coo-ed at you, my beautiful boy." She drank.

Earlier, there had been the greeting, Draco's shock as Professor - no, Headmistress - McGonagall re-introduced him with his long dead mother. Her confusion as memory charms faded away, then more anguish at the lost years. There had been joy, but joy mixed with anger. McGonagall had quickly brought them back to Hogwarts, and then they'd taken the Floo network home.

"And now you are at Hogwarts...on your first great adventure. You must tell me everything, and quickly, because in three months I will lose you again." Narcissa saw Draco's control; there was no pained look. Lucius could hide his emotions from everyone but me. She looked around, reached into her robes (kept in her closet for years, unmoved except for a weekly cleaning) and drew out her wand.

"Lumos! Lumos! That's better" she said, putting her wand away. The pictures on the walls let out a small exclamation. Lord Montavian Malfoy, Father's Grandfather, who'd purchased the first insurance contract sold by Gringotts days before a group of Griffyindors slew his prized Hungarian Horntail, awoke with a snort. Draco looked around. He'd grown up in Malfoy Manor and the dining hall had always been cloaked in shadows, never bright. Noon outside meant dusk in the dining hall. He couldn't see the heraldry at night. Father always told him he needed darkness to plan carefully. But now …. he had so many secrets he wanted, he needed to share. And so does she.

"Tell me about Father." Draco pulled his knees up to his chest and clutched them to him with his hands.

"After you were born, your father's wand glowed silver for a month, and he seemed to fly up and down the stairs."

Day turned to evening, and evening to night and morning with stories traded between mother and son, as they talked of her husband and his father and discovered the truth that was somewhere between the two.

June 26th

Draco opened the door and bowed low. "Madam Goyle. Madam Crabbe." He nodded at Gregory and Vincent, who stood slightly behind, and they nodded back. "Please, do come in." His mother's voice sang out from the dining room "Adrasteia! Tabitha! It has been so long!" Draco backed away and swept his arm low and across, gesturing for his friend's mothers to enter.

"Vincent, you should take lessons in manners from Lord Malfoy," said Madam Crabbe, her voice not steady. "Draco … you are becoming more and more like Lucius ..." she bowed her head and rushed past him, robes swishing noisily. Her voice brightened "Narcissa! When I heard …. I daren't hope it was true …." Madam Goyle was slightly past him when she stopped, turned back to him and squatted so that she's looking up to me, not down at me Draco thought automatically. "I am so sorry about your Father, Draco." He didn't try to stop the tears.

"We all lost someone, Madam Goyle, and I am the only one who gained." She hugged him quickly, wiped the single tear from his face, smiled, and then went inside. Draco paused, then stepped outside and closed the door behind him.

"Aren't we going inside?" Vincent asked.

Gregory leaned against the wall, shaking his head "Do you really want to?" He raised an eyebrow.

Draco gathered his robes carefully and sat down on the steps. "How are you two doing?" This had been the first time they'd been able to see each other, outside of funerals and wakes. Vincent shrugged, and sat down next to Draco.

"We're alone," said Vincent. "I mean, it's not like before school. You had friends and family. Now we've lost family and all of our friends are avoiding us, because we lost our fathers. When I went to Diagon Alley last week …. it's like we weren't there."

"It's hard" said Gregory. "I get sad, and then angry." He picked up some pebbles and started throwing them down the path. "I wake up and I feel normal for a second, happy, and then I remember and I'm angry at myself." Vincent took out his wand and started casting at each passing pebble, Ma-ha-su, mostly missing but barely. Draco was impressed, given the size and speed, but just nodded. Gregory picked up another handful of rocks and continued "Some days I think I'm not mad enough. I'm just kind of drifting along. Should I be sadder? Happier?"

"I know," Draco replied as a sharp Ping Sent a pebble veering off into the nearby trees. "Nice. I'm used to having a mask, like Father taught. But I can't tell if I'm wearing it enough, or too much." Laughter came from inside the house. After a moment, Gregory continued lazily throwing.

"Does it bother you?" Gregory asked. Draco gave him a look. "That they are laughing?"

Draco thought about it. "A bit. But it's like you said. You should be sadder, but sometimes you aren't. So I can't really get angry." He shrugged. What had it been called? Right. The Fundamental Attribution Error. "They're reuniting. It's happy. We can't be what the world expects to see all the time. Why expect our Mothers to be? They need a break as much as we do."

"Yes," said Vincent as his latest spell passed just behind the last rock. "We do." He sat down on the other side of Draco, crossed his left leg over his right. He scratched his neck with his wand before it disappeared back inside his robe. "Any plans for the rest of the summer?"

"I have to go through Father's papers." Gregory shot Vincent a surprised look. Lord Malfoy kept notes? "Nothing like that. Formal contracts, business arrangements. Its tedious. And studying. I've got to be ready for Defence this year. I've been reading about Wars."

"Grindelwald, or older stuff?"

"Muggle wars, mainly."

Vincent had, by this point, laid down completely and was staring at the sky. A passing cloud, shaped like a sneering hippogriff, hinted of rainfall in the near future. "Why muggle wars? I mean, Dragon Army could probably defeat most muggle armies. And if not now, in a few years."

Draco nodded. He'd been thinking that, too. As he read about Thermopylae, Jutland, The Tet Offensive, Bunker Hill, Iwo Jima. "Why could we defeat them, Vince?" Gregory stopped in mid throw.

"Magic" they said together.

Draco shook his head. "I don't think so." He raised his hands in surrender. "Yes. But not just that. If we fought a muggle army, they wouldn't know what we could do. We could apparate and disapparate. Adults could anyway. We could confound them, stupefy them. We'd have broomsticks. It would be a rout." Draco got up and started pacing. "But it's not the magic that makes it the rout. Look at what happened in all of our battles. Each armies magic is roughly the same." Vincent started to say something and Draco waved a hand, "with the houses split up we all had mudbloods" No point opening that can of worms just yet "and strong wizards and witches. We're better at Magic than Potter, even Granger is; but Potter won more often. Why?"

"Because nobody has any idea what he's going to do" muttered Gregory. Vincent nodded.

"Right!" said Draco. "Two muggle armies know what they can do to each other. But if they face Wizards … they don't know! Every battle last year - every single one - was won or lost by surprise. Granger's army played dead in the first battle, Potter surprised them with that sunlight potion that decimated Sunshine Regiment, but we out-surprised him then. We knew what was coming," Gregory looked at him sharply and Draco smiled. "Well, we knew enough. So, no surprise. Our gloves. That potion of liquid night during the broomstick fight. The suits of armor. Everything in the lake with all those stupid plots... "

"Not all the battles, Boss" said Vincent. "Diggory's victory in the Great Hall?"

Draco considered it. "OK, that's the exception that proves the rule. And sometimes history works that way too. Sometimes you get generals who just plod along, and then the better army wins. You can win by just being better and out preparing them. But it's safer to surprise them. Even V..." Draco's voice dropped. "Even You-Know-Who got tricked. Professor Quirrell was good, and maybe could have won if he was healthy. But something surprised Voldemort," Vincent flinched slightly, Draco pretended not to notice, "something got him. He went through our fathers, all of the Death Eaters without a scratch. Even Quirrell died. But something surprised him, and he lost too."

Draco kept pacing. Once you say it out loud its obvious. But what could surprise him? Maybe Quirrell set a trap and his entire attack was a distraction … Draco frowned, then shook his head. He remembered a lesson from his father. He could even hear it in his Father's voice Speculating when you do not have any information is a child's game, my son.

"Dumbledore?" said Vincent, not caring if Draco was annoyed. "He was crazy, but even You Know Who was scared of him." Draco started pacing again, unable to shake a feeling in his gut. It was Potter. I don't know how, but...

Ludicrous said his inner Lucius. The boy is a mad genius, but that is too much. You underestimate Voldemort.

"Nah," said Gregory, "Dumbledore was dead. Probably the same time as Flamel. Draco's right. Quirrell gave some trap to Granger. She hit him with it once they both came back..."

Look at the actual results and see who benefits, Draco thought.

Lucius got quiet. You may be right, my son. But we have no way to know.

Vincent shook his head. "The Professor was a Slytherin's Slytherin, sure. But he wouldn't do that."

"Sure he would, she was a General. Killing her was a personal insult" replied Gregory.

Draco sighed. "In ANY case," he said. "If I read Muggle History that Potter's already studied, he'll have less to surprise me with this year. There are a ton of good ideas. Muggles may not know much, but they fought a lot of wars. And you notice patterns: How important it is to be able to communicate during a fight, to have good information, to have troops trained to work together. We learned all of that, even in a few battles, but if you start to look at hundreds of them you see lots of tricks. I don't want to have to discover everything ourselves. There's not enough time."

Draco paused for breath, "So even if Potter manages to, I don't know, Imperius the Giant Squid or something" That's actually a good idea, and forgivable too, I think "we'll at least smash Sunshine Regiment."

Vincent and Gregory froze, all camaraderie gone, rigidly formal. Draco saw the shift from relaxed friends to minions. Anxious minions. Draco glanced back and forth between them.

"What?" he said, his voice steady. Just then the head elf, a good hand taller than all of the other elves in Malfoy Manor, appeared with a poof and bowed to Draco.

"Mistress says that Young Lord and guests should come in for dinner." The elf didn't stand up from his bow, but shot a glance at Draco as he stood, frozen.

"What?" Draco said louder, voice preternaturally steady, lest it crack.

"Mistress says..."

"Not you!" he snapped. The elf, still bowed, disappeared with the sound of wet lightning.

Gregory took a deep breath. "You haven't been following the Prophet?" Draco shook his head. There had been too many funerals, and the aftermath of Voldemort's death and business papers and days and days lost where he hadn't gotten out of bed at all. Those were past, but he hadn't caught up and the Prophet could run itself for a while.

Vincent looked him in the eye. "Granger sacked Azkaban."

Dinner had been a slow, loud affair. As a child dinner parties bored Draco. Father had great plots, but Draco hadn't been involved, except in minor ways, plots he recognized now as disposable training devices. Still, Draco's education had been exhaustive from as soon as he could walk and talk and the more details he remembered and recited at breakfast, the better his chances for ice cream. At parties, Draco's boredom never dulled his eyesight. His attention. He'd mingle, chatting some but listening always. Once, when he was six, he'd discovered an elderly french witch in a closet with Olivander's assistant. That earned him ice cream for a week; although he hadn't understood why until last October.

"Tabitha," said Mother, "Draco tells me that Gregory is the best flyer in the year." Dinner had been a decidedly simple affair, roast beast with plain gravy, steamed vegetables, wine (butterbeer for the boys), and bread.

Madam Goyle smiled broadly, but no teeth showed. Her hair, which had been done up in a tightly wrapped braid under her hat, now had one loose black hair hanging slightly out to the side. "Oh, yes, we'd heard. We were quite sure he was going to make the Quidditch team..."

Madam Crabbe nodded "I don't agree with a lot of what passes for education these days, but those armies are much better than that silly game anyway, isn't that right boys?" They all quickly agreed. "Gregory's stories about the battles are quite exciting, fighting in Draco's army."

"Well," Narcissa replied quickly, "Draco had good help."

"Oh no, that Professor mixed the houses up even made that mudblood girl a general," replied Madam Crabbe.

"Standards have fallen" sniffed Madam Goyle, and all the ladies nodded.

Draco listened to the conversation, getting considerably more confused, boredom forgotten. This conversation felt different. There was the game of names, of course, subtle shifts of politeness. But there was something more, something he'd never seen at Father's parties. This is the strangest conversation I've ever seen. The chit-chat continued, each woman pleading how difficult things had been for her, or her son, and praising the other two families. Draco mulled it over, answering questions politely when asked, no different from Gregory or Vincent, in this situation. Just a boy at Mother's side.

He listened for several more minutes, after Tabitha implored Gregory to "tell how Draco outwitted the Boy-Who-Lived in that battle in the woods" when Draco put words to his feelings. It's a dominance contest, but in reverse. They are all humbling themselves … as a sign of friendship. He thought about it and it explained everything. Father had said women play the Game differently. Draco relaxed. There would be times he'd have to fight, to maintain the position of House Malfoy.

But not today.

He listened to Gregory's story, surprised at how a story he knew, he'd lived, could sound so different. Gregory's point of view didn't minimize Draco's importance, but he'd seen such a different aspect of it, scouting while Draco cast spell after spell, that some of the turns surprised him. The bitterness of his personal defeat (not mentioned at all, of course) felt easy to swallow months later, especially when Draco considered that he'd been vanquished by the Girl-Who-Revived, by the Girl with a Phoenix. He found himself laughing while following the story, as Vincent and Gregory argued about who really stunned Hannah Abbott, if Dean Thomas had really ridden a centaur to outflank his second squadron or just stumbled on them in surprise and a cross fire of useless Somnium spells. Draco relaxed and truly enjoyed the party, happy to be among friends for the first time in a month.

He'd deal with problems another day. Miss Granger wasn't his enemy. Not really. But she was certainly Draco's problem. Draco Malfoy could be content with second place.

Desert (pie and vanilla ice cream) had been brought out when there was a knock at the door. Draco got up and answered it. (The other two started to get up, but he just shook his head slightly). As the door opened Draco saw the uniform first, the person wearing it second. He nodded, smiled and bowed, a small delay to remember the names the Auror had, and which name was correct. He went by Li at Hogwarts...

"Auror Li. To what do I owe the pleasure?" A formulaic greeting he'd heard any number of times. Etiquette has many uses, Father said, but filling awkward silences and stalling are the two most important.

"Lord Malfoy." The Auror bowed, slightly compared to the formality of his words, "I am sorry, but there have been a bit too many instances of under-age magic detected here in the last hour."

Draco opened the door and beckoned Li in, "I apologize, sir. Mr. Crabbe, Mr. Goyle and myself were showing off for our mothers." He made sure that his words carried. "With all of the troubles of the last month, it just slipped our minds. I'm sure you understand." Draco followed the Auror into the dining room where Li bowed, deeply this time.

"Madam Malfoy. Forgive the intrusion. Boys?" he held out his hand. Draco quickly took out his wand and handed it over. Vincent and Gregory got up slowly and complied as well. Father bribed the Aurors to overlook this. All of his words about how Malfoy Manor was not subject to this law had been true of course; but Draco had never thought about why that had been true.

As Vincent placed the third wand in the Auror's hand, Li took out his own wand, pointed it a Vincent's.

"Prior Incantato," said Li. Draco's face fell into polite mask number one by the time the words were finished. Li looked at Vincent "I'm not familiar with that spell."

"Professor Quirrell taught it early in the year" said Gregory.

"For practicing aiming" said Vincent. The Auror nodded, and quickly cast again on the other two wands.

Mother saw it, the look on Auror Li's face when he examined Draco's wand. He paused. "I don't think I need to confiscate these. No harm in practicing, but …." he just placed the wands back on the table and bowed again. "My apologies for the intrusion, Lord Malfoy"

Everyone saw the look the Auror shot Draco when he walked by.

"Have a pleasant day, sir." Draco walked him back to the door, making sure he wasn't quite out of earshot when he said "I am sure we can continue my father's arrangement where I practice under strict supervision, if you can recommend a tutor..."

By the time he returned to the table, a minute later, the conversation had started back up again. Draco told and listened to stories, but now he was considering several problems, the least of which was how to get around the restrictions on underage magic for the rest of the summer. He idly played with his ice cream which he no longer desired as he had before Hogwarts. Now he had real problems, real goals. Draco still liked ice cream, but associated it with childish pursuits, and he couldn't enjoy it at the moment.

June 30th

"Augusta" said Mother, as Madam Longbottom pushed past the startled waiter and sat down at the table. She snapped and pointed to the empty setting in front of her, and the waiter scurried to get fresh plates.

"Narcissa. Lord Malfoy. What are you wearing?" Narcissa was wearing a simple black robe with purple trim. Purple was the new rage, although this robe happened to be nearly fifteen years old. Draco wore a bespoke suit, charcoal with green tie kept neatly in place with a silver snake clip.

"Good afternoon, Madam Longbottom" said Draco politely. "It is a muggle outfit. I have business in London after lunch." He'd bought the suit several weeks ago, the better to blend in. He'd learned this outfit would blend perfectly in their world …. when he turned twenty. After that disastrous outing he'd taken to wearing blue jeans and an atrocious orange jacket with hood and pullstrings, which looked terrible but was the correct fashion for children in that strange world. Comfortable, though. Mother liked the suit though, so he wore that until he was alone. And, although he'd never admit it, he liked the suit as well.

"Don't let me keep you, dears. I just wanted to say hello."

"Augusta." Mother looked around, but the restaurant was mostly empty and what few patrons were there were looking at the couple going into Mary's Room. "There is no need for false hospitality."

Madam Longbottom took off her hat, her hair a mess underneath. "I offer none. You know I loathed Lucius. Do you know he only ever said two true things to me his whole life apart from his name? But we widows must stick together to survive. That bond I understand all too well." By now some settings had arrived and she poured herself a glass of tea. "And as for Lord Malfoy and I, why we have an even rarer bond."

"We do?" Draco blurted out.

"We got someone back. That almost never happens. Now with the Ministry having discovered Merlin's Chalice, I suppose it will happen more often."

The Daily Prophet had been ablaze for the last several weeks starting with the story of how Amelia Bones, the Director of Magical Law Enforcement had discovered Lord Voldemort's notes detailing various artifacts that could restore him to full power. This explained how You-Know-Who had been defeated so easily by a school girl, albeit "the most powerful witch her age any teacher could recall" according to Headmistress McGonagall. Lord Voldemort had returned to life, but had just started his quest to return to his full power. The article went on to discuss how Director Bones had carefully pieced together the notes with cryptic clues and hints left by Dumbledore. Put together those led her to the resting place of the Chalice. The story described how she and her Aurors had recovered it with minimal loss of limbs that could now, thanks to the Chalice, be fully healed and restored.

A few days later the Prophet reported that a middle-aged DMLE Bones had presented the discovery (but not the Chalice itself) to the Wizengamot. You could still tell it was her in the pictures, although she was less angular than her older self she gave no indication of softness. After the announcement the Cures had started a trickle but now hundreds of people had been saved at Hogwarts (technically the Peverell Hospital located adjacent to Hogwarts) by Merlin's Chalice which reversed aging and healed the sick.

And the insane, apparently. Draco noticed that story confused him, but continued the conversation.

"Neville's parents are fine? I hadn't realized that the Chalice could cure ..." he stopped as Madam Longbottom nodded, blowing on her tea to cool it.

"We've lived through terrible days." said Narcissa, "I'm glad we can now live through days of wonder."

"Indeed" said Augusta. "Once all the truly old people have gone through, I expect I'll have a go." She chuckled softly at something. "But I just sat down here, forgive me, to offer my condolences and to tell Lord Malfoy something." Draco waited patiently.

Seeing no response, Augusta continued "You know, last year during the … confusion, some parents and members of the Board of Governors stopped in at Hogwarts and witnessed one of David Monroe's battles. Fought by first years, no less." She said, between sips of tea.

"It was fascinating, Narcissa. If Draco is shy, you must press him to open up about those armies. And if you have told your mother, Draco, I'd love to hear about them. Someday. But in any case, Young General Malfoy earned quite a lot of praise from David Monroe."

Draco blinked. Professor Quirrell had praised him? Publicly?

"Oh, he had criticism too, but said Draco's mistakes were merely signs that he was still young."

"As he is," said Narcissa, "although not as young as I remember him." She smiled.

"It was during this battle that your Father said the second truthful thing. I thought you'd like to hear it. Your army won the battle, but Lucius took your … personal defeat ... badly. So he probably didn't ever say it to you."

"What did he tell you, Madam Longbottom?"

"Oh, he didn't tell me. He told everyone. He said," and here she put down her cup and stared at Draco, "'He will be the greatest Lord Malfoy that ever lived.'"

They all sat quietly.

"I know your anguish, Draco. I know your training was harsh; set to impossible standards, and now you've lost your Father." She started to get up, and reached for her coat. "But know that, even if he didn't show it, he loved you and was fiercely proud."

"Thank you Madam Longbottom. I know he loved me; but … I'd never heard him say it to anyone else." Augusta put her hat back on her head, secured it with a firm pat, then took her leave.

Author's note (5/5/15) – This update fixes a few typos. In particular I always that it was Diraclaw, not Diricawl. I thought about leaving the typo and introducing a new creature, but for now I fixed it.

Also, thanks to Redditors at r/hpmor, for nitpicking. r/hpmor, for all your HPMOR needs.

Additionally, Thanks to the guest who pointed out that Augusta misremembered the quote by Lucius Malfoy in Chapter 78. (The original says "has yet lived" instead of "ever lived.") I've decided to keep my (misremembered) wording because a) people's memories are not exact and b) it seems like the kind of detail that's easy to get wrong. Since, you know, I got it wrong

Chapter 2: Social Gatherings, Pt 2

The door's knocker looked so menacing, so convincingly like a Krait poised to strike, that Harry James Potter-Evans-Verres unconsciously paused before grabbing it and pounding the door three times. He turned to the assembled adults.

"It won't be as bad as the Headmistress thinks," Harry said.

Petunia and Michael exchanged worried glances on the doorstep of Malfoy Manor. As Muggles, Harry had told them they wouldn't normally be able to see Malfoy Manor, much less approach it. But the formal invitation in their hands, elegantly lettered and addressed, tamed the wards. Professor McGonagall had offered to join them; Harry had declined. Michael thought the house looked like the Haunted Mansion - black structures stacked hodge-podge on top of each other with no right angles between walls, the only rectangle being the main door and the only squares being a few windows. Petunia, looking at it, just shuddered.

Michael Evans-Verres smiled nervously. His son had matured over the last year, but his social skills still trailed behind other children.

After a second, Hermione spoke up. "Maybe they didn't hear. It's a big house."

Beside her, Leo Granger harrumphed slightly.

"I'm not sure this is such a good idea," he said for the fourth time. Hermione kept her mouth shut and shifted her backpack nervously. Your parents are allowed to worry because you died. Things hadn't been awkward when she came back; her parents were too surprised and grateful. They'd gotten awkward later, after a few days. Then they'd noticed her teeth.

Harry reached for the knocker again as the door flew open. Everyone started to say hello, but only one person finished.

"Honored guests, come in! Come in!" said the small creature standing in front of them, dressed in what looked like a burlap sack. His large eyes beamed at the entourage; long ears flopped as he nodded enthusiastically.

Roberta recovered first. "We brought some wine...," she started to say but the creature's eyes, already cartoonish, grew wider and she lost her nerve.

"Brought wine! They dare ..." it hissed, then paused with a look of horror "Mustn't insult guests! Bad Dobby! Bad Dobby!" The elf turned and pounded his face into the door frame with surprising force.

"What is that?" said Michael Evans-Verres, turning to the children. Hermione was trying to persuade the elf to stop in slightly frantic tones, when Harry answered.

"It's a house elf. We have them at Hogwarts, but I've never seen one act like this." He ignored a particularly sickening crunch as Dobby's head rebounded off the door frame. Harry heard Draco shouting "Dobby! Back to the kitchen!" and the elf disappeared with a whampf right before his head impacted the doorway. There was a sound of bowls crashing, followed by one bowl ringing as it rolled slowly to a stop.

Draco rushed out, smiling. "I'm sorry. Please, come in." Draco bowed low.

"Mum, Dad" said Harry. "This is Draco Malfoy. Draco, my parents Michael Evans-Verres and Petunia Verres-Evans." Michael shook hands with the boy, who stood slightly taller than Harry, and examined him. Draco had slicked back blonde hair a few brushes shy of perfection. He wore simple black robes and a slightly off-center cape, clasped with a silver snake. There were a few specks of dust on his cape, but the boy radiated calmness and poise more than any child he'd ever met.

Except Hermione Granger, Michael thought. Must be a magical thing.

"Are we early, Draco?" asked Petunia, shaking his hand. Michael glanced at his watch, 7:01pm.

"It's my fault" said Draco smoothly. "I didn't think to tell Harry about it. You're still on Hogwarts time, aren't you?"

"Isn't Hogwarts in the same time zone?" asked Roberta.

Muggles control zones of time? Draco thought to himself, horrified for a brief second before he realized it was just an expression.

"Trains" muttered Michael to Harry, who nodded.

Petunia looked at them and said "What do trains have to do with this?"

Trains, as Michael and Harry knew, led the impetus behind formalizing time. To be sure, ships had led the way, but travel by ship was measured in weeks, not days or hours. Before trains, every village and every town had its main clock with no coordination between towns required. Only with industrialization, with the need to precisely coordinate movement of items across vast distances, did people make agreements when noon (or a dinner party) should occur.

So it made sense that magicians, who had never industrialized, wouldn't have agreed on precise standards for time across multiple locations. No spells said "Start at 11:30," they all referred to noon, sunset, midnight, and other times with specific physical meanings. Actually, thought Harry, they probably do have agreements, but I've never had an exact appointment scheduled outside of Hogwarts.

"Draco, these are my parents the Doctors Leo and Roberta Granger. Mum, Dad, This is Draco Malfoy."

There was swishing of robes down the hallway as a young, smiling woman came forward. "Draco, do introduce me to your friends and their parents."

"Of course Mother." Introductions were made all around. Draco had warned Mother that there would be misunderstandings and to just assume any social blunder was made in ignorance instead of malice, so he didn't mention the gifts. But there were limits, so after handshakes were made, and Draco had accepted the various bottles of wine, deserts, and flowers and set them in the dining room table, he continued the conversation.

"We were just discussing, Mother, that Muggle time doesn't work exactly like our time." Roberta Granger glanced around the room and let out a soft moan as she saw a grandfather clock at 6:50.

"Lily never mentioned anything like this" said Petunia.

"Oh yes, Draco said you are Lily's sister." Narcissa said, offering seats to everyone. "I must admit I don't see the resemblance. You are lovely, like she was, but in a different way…. Lily reminded me of spring, but you seem more like a northern summer." Draco slowly released his breath. Mother would be fine. Father had always said Mother possessed a natural social grace; but he'd been worried for the first few weeks. Narcissa's prior awkwardness had been the pain of discovering her baby grown and husband dead. Now Draco felt confident that Mother would ever-so-gently steer the conversation towards common ground. She'd already mentioned a mutual acquaintance with Harry's mother although Merlin knew how she'd find anything in common with Hermione's parents.

As Dobby and the other elves brought out the food, Narcissa put the empty wine goblet down. "This is surprisingly good wine, Roberta" And there it is, thought Draco.

"Why, thank you. I don't have much experience, but the sommelier recommended it..."

"Do wizards use magic to make wine?" asked Harry. "I know we can't transfigure it, but is there anything in Herbology about helping grapes grow?"

"Why can't you Transfigure it?" whispered Leo quietly.

"All Herbology lessons dealt with magical plants, but that could just mean it isn't taught at schools." Narcissa said, reflecting on what she knew about Muggles. "It wouldn't be an appropriate subject for children, though."

"It will change back later after you drink it, Dad" whispered Hermione.

"Well, then in that case," said Harry's father, "Muggle wine is probably, on average, about as good as Wizard wine. And since there are so many more Muggle wine makers..."

"Dad, wizards could enchant the soil and tightly control the environment, not even considering..."

Leo blanched "So even simple magic is dangerous?"

"Do many Muggles make wine?" asked Narcissa.

"I don't think that many do," said Roberta, "but Hermione says there just aren't that many wizards and witches."

"Harry, even if you assume that the average wizard wine is better, the sample space and standard deviation practically ensures that the best wines will be ours." said Michael.

"Dad," Hermione whispered, "Transfiguration the most complicated magic. Can we talk about this later?"

"It's true," said Draco, "the Muggle world is surprising. Muggles aren't like plays depict them." His London excursions confirmed that. Did Harry set this up. Is he investigating mother's beliefs, to see if she's ... reformed? It would make sense. Mother had married a prominent Death Eater, after all.

"Ours?" Harry raised an eyebrow. He'd practiced for a year before he could just raise one. "You sound like a football fan. It's not a competition." Petunia glared at the men in her family, to no avail.

"You can imagine why we worry, Hermione..." Leo said as everyone took their seats.

Michael, who had shown Harry literature on sports fan psychology, ignored the barb. "I agree. That's why I'm pointing out trade opportunities. Both worlds' standards of living could rise dramatically..."

"Of course I've thought of that, but we have to ease into it. Remember Dobby?"

"This is a lovely plate of food, Narcissa," said Petunia warily.

"Yes, Mother, the lamb chop looks delicious." Draco piped in cheerily as he cut a small piece off, trying to force all the conversations back to a single topic. Draco didn't particularly care for lamb, but he'd seen it on menus posted outside high end muggle restaurants, so he'd suggested it instead of the Dragon Tartare Father served. All things considered, this is going well.

Wine, Time Zones, amusing differences in etiquette, and other conversation topics flowed with the wine. Narcissa's offer to show Malfoy Manor was, of course, politely accepted and so the parents were gone when the house elves started removing the plates and cleaning up.

"Draco, can I ask Dobby some questions?" asked Hermione. A look of horror crossed Dobby's face but he continued picking up dishes, each one disappearing with a small poof as he grabbed it.

"Of course," said Draco. "Dobby," he said firmly. Dobby sighed and turned around.

"Dobby would be happy to answer," he said morosely. He stood waiting.

"Why did you hurt yourself, Dobby?" she asked.

"Dobby must be punished! For insulting guests!" Dobby looked confused.

"Who made that rule?"

"Dobby … Dobby doesn't know. It's always been that rule."

"Hermione, they are house elves" said Draco. "It's what they do. They enjoy it." Harry shot Draco a look. "Oh come on, they do. I've only ever heard Dobby complain about one thing."

"Dobby never complains, young master! Oooh, bad Dobby!" Dobby rushed towards a table leg. Draco snapped his fingers.

"Dobby, stop." Draco's voice was calm. "Tell them your complaint. It's fine."

Dobby, eyes downcast, shrank into himself, then flashed an apologetic look to Draco. "Dobby likes Young Master and Mistress. But Old Master, when Mistress was gone … Old Master ..." Dobby sputtered, looked longingly at the table leg, then lowered his voice to a hiss, "... forbade us ..." Dobby sobbed a few breaths, "from cleaning Mistresses Room!"

"It's ok, Dobby. Things are better. The room is nice and clean now, isn't it."

Dobby, sniffing, wiped his noise on his sleeve. "Oh yes, Master!" Draco waved his hand back to the table and Dobby, with a quick bow, went back to removing the silverware.

"There. You see?" said Draco.

Even Harry smiled. "Whoever made them was evil, but ..." he shrugged. "They seem happy." He turned to Draco, "She was going on about liberating House Elves all summer."

Draco smiled. "First Azkaban. Then … Kitchens Everywhere!" Hermione frowned.

"S.P.H.E.W. – The Society for the Protection of House Elf Workers?" said the Boy-Who-Lived and Draco started laughing.

"It's not funny" she fumed. Draco kept laughing. She shook her head, hair flowing perfectly back and forth "I thought we were here to discuss lesson plans." Draco's chuckling slowed. Harry wiped his eye. Hermione reach into her backpack and pulled eight lengthy scrolls and some loose papers which she passed to Draco. "These scrolls are my notes." She glared at Harry. "If you have anything to add..."

Draco took them carefully, setting some on the clean table to get the rest. "The papers aren't yours, Harry?" Draco knew Muggles preferred loose paper to scrolls.

"Professor Quirrel's lesson plan for first years" said Harry quietly. "They found them in his things." Draco gasped, while Harry continued. "It's not a spellbook. It's just notes on what he thought was appropriate for first years, which spells to teach, which lessons to teach after typical mistakes, rough drafts of speeches. It won't make sense to anyone who hasn't had the course, these aren't notes, more like …. reminders." And Voldemort practicing thinking like David Monroe pretending to be Quirrell.

"Wow. He had notes for each year?" Harry nodded as Draco glanced through the papers.

Draco reluctantly set the notes aside. He'd read later, when there were no guests. "I don't know why you need me for this." He looked at Harry, but it was Hermione who spoke up.

"There's an awful lot of stories going around. Awful rumours. It's going to be awkward for everyone. I wasn't around but I know you worked quite hard. After I..." Hermione couldn't make eye contact. "We were all Generals, fair and square. You deserve this is much as we do."

"More," said Harry.

Draco nodded. "I'll look at your notes later and send an owl with thoughts." There was no rush, it was only July. After a pause he asked "Can a Patronus find someone hidden?"

Hermione shook her head. "I don't think so."

Harry continued "That makes sense, otherwise Aurors could always track people down." He paused, "Now that you mention it, I wonder how they find people who want to be found..." he trailed off, lost in thought. "Typically people tell them where to look..."

"Who are you looking for?" Hermione asked. Harry was barely paying attention. Draco shrugged.

"Snape." He paused for a second, but when there was no question he continued. "Harry and I are … reforming Slytherin." Hermione's eyes widened.

Harry, eyes still closed, quietly said "He'd approve, but he won't come back."

Draco nodded. "This is a bad time. So many of us lost parents. I know most of the families, but I don't know them well. Without Father … there's going to be a power struggle. Struggles. Not just adults. And I ..." he shrugged. "I could use the information he has. He'd know who was sympathetic. He'd know when I'd be wasting my time."

It's not fair to say this conversation caused a war to stir inside of Hermione. But it caused a small skirmish. By now she'd recovered and asked "What about Professor Slughorn?"

Draco shook his head. "Outside the school, yes. Inside? He knows less than I do. By all accounts he's fairly aloof, except for his favorites. He may know more about the families, but he hasn't even met most of the students."

Harry opened his eyes. "I'll try to send a message to Snape. I can take out advertisements but I don't think..." he trailed off as the adults came galoomphing down the stairs. Narcissa was staring at him and she said "Oh, Draco ..."

and Harry felt the dagger in his head, no fire, pain, just a careful opening of his thoughts and memories. My son is my heart … the dagger paused briefly … Allies? Allies! … now moving again … I want to see if you can learn the Patronus Charm …. thoughts flashed quickly as Harry set defenses around his private life My hand wasn't working … Harry realized that he didn't need to shield everything, Narcissa wasn't looking for details about Harry, except as they related to Draco … does the rest of that matter, my son? No, father. …. Dumbledore burned her to death. As quickly and quietly as it entered, the knife left

"...could you please have Dobby bring desserts? I assume you kids want some as well" said Narcissa, smiling at them all.

Harry Potter piped up "Yes, please!" sounding like a normal eleven year old boy for the first time all evening.

Author's note (5/5) – Thank you all for the kind words, but here and on reddit.

Update (5/6) - Typo update, and I had some confused writing (I'll blame last minute edits). I've updated Narcissa's comment on wine and Draco's thoughts starting with "It's true."

Chapter 6: Efficient Sorting Algorithms

Draco sat comfortably at the Slytherin table staring up into the dusk sky. Clouds drifted lazily from the North and birds, starlings mostly, darted around. Draco watched the flock expand and contract, thoughts drifting through conversations, weighing potential allies and enemies. Vincent and Gregory's position took up some thoughts, as did recent lessons from his diary, and his earlier conversations on the train. Draco wasn't thinking just remembering and idly considering connections that popped into his head.

Draco's thoughts drifted like clouds above.

Draco had already studied the head table, seating arrangements told a story. At the center sat Minerva McGonagall, black hair flowing freely under her still stern hat. Professors Sprout and Flitwick flanked her. The Headmistress chatted with both, gazing solemnly over the assembled students. On the other side of Flitwick sat Horace Slughorn, leaning over his own belly to chortle as he pointed out entering students to the bored Charms instructor. Beside Sprout sat a man whose deeply scarred right cheek marred an otherwise handsome look. His red and gold robes (and seat) announced the new Head of Gryffindor. Draco didn't recognize him. Other professors sat on wings of the head table. Professor Burbage looked annoyed sitting next to a young-ish Muggle dressed in an oddly styled suit. The lapels were much wider, colors much bolder than suits Draco encountered.. The Muggle's wild black hair, thick plastic glasses and lush mutton chop sideburns looked like nothing Draco had seen in his admitted limited experience. Certainly no teenager he'd met dressed like that.

After taking in the head table, Draco glanced around the house tables. Slytherin's sparseness bothered him so he stared at the sky instead.

The room quieted when the First Years entered, led by Hagrid. Draco's eyes drifted earthward and noticed that the Headmistress already standing. He hadn't heard. She gazed down at the procession of children, barely smaller but much less confident than Second Years. Had it really only been one year? First years waved at siblings and drew themselves close into small groups under the withering inspection of the older students who whispered, jeered, and made clandestine bets. The Sorting Hat, placed on a small stool in front of the head table sat silent until the children filled in the gaps between the tables and stopped.

A small rip in the cloth revealed itself to the gasp of the First Years, and the Hat spoke.

.

I'm the cleverest piece of leather

ever formed into a hat

And I've stayed the same forever

Though I change my annual chat.

.

Since the cornerstone was placed

upon the ground to start our school

The yearly opening feast must wait

while I declaim atop this stool!

.

Should you be in Ravenclaw

you'll answer riddles by the door,

For sharpening the student's mind

was Rowena's favorite chore.

.

If you land in Hufflepuff,

then you'll never lack a friend,

For Helga was the glue

that held together till the end.

.

If 'tis Slytherin you seek,

then your reward you must chase

For the virtue of ambition

surely drew you to their place

.

And every Gryffindor does know

that the path righteous and true

demands the utmost bravery -

Nothing else at all will do.

.

But I have a secret request

That I choose now to reveal:

Consider those whose grand bequest

created Hogwart's Mighty Seal.

.

Look closely at our Founders -

consider their full history -

You'll find extended meanings

and glimpse a subtle mystery.

.

For Rowena was ambitious,

And Salazar was brave,

And Godric fiercely loyal,

Helga clever to her grave.

.

Each founder has more character

than we remember every day

Do not oversimplify the

complex virtues they display.

.

What use is noble bravery

if you cannot tell what's right?

.

What will you do with cleverness

when you've lost the will to fight?

.

How will your true ambition taste

when you're lonely at the end?

.

And if you do nothing at all

Who would want you as a friend?

.

Tho' our Founders have their virtues

Each exhibits certain flaws

Yet my magic is constrained

to Sorting strictly by their Laws.

.

So I am a simple top piece

Bound to my appointed task.

You can ponder, you can question;

That is from all of you I ask.

.

Know Thyself! For You are Deeper

than the Sorting I do voice,

I am not your only Keeper

You do daily get a Choice.

.

Hear me Teachers! Hear me Students!

I do finish now my Song.

Those who state opinions firmly

May still be completely wrong.

.

When the Hat began the hall sat rapt and silent, first years stunned by the Hat itself, everyone else by the message. When the Hat named each House their table cheered (not too loud, everyone knows the Hat does not pause). As the song continued into the founder's flaws whispering started. Professor Slughorn looked nervous; might the Hat dare abolish Slytherin altogether? The murmurs rose until the Headmistress' harsh Shhshh quieted everyone.

As the last word resounded in a silent hall, Draco looked around. Scattered claps sounded after a few seconds, nothing like the rambunctious applause after last year's song. What had the hat meant? The Hat had reminded him that each Founder possessed virtues the others espoused. Why?

Professor Flitwick, holding a scroll, said "Creevey, Colin" and Draco's eyes snapped back to the Sorting, all polite attention. The Hat had said 'Yet my magic is constrained.' The Hat chose. That's what it did. Colin went into Ravenclaw. Draco focused on the words as several other students got chosen. One went into Slytherin, which distracted Draco as he clapped and tried to remember the boy's name. That wasn't a good sign. The hat picked the dominant virtue; everyone had a mix of virtues; the Hat did its best. Draco's thinking went in circles.

The blond girl - so that was Luna Lovegood - went to Ravenclaw. Draco snorted.

The Hat admitted it could be wrong. It couldn't come out and say "I'm wrong, sometimes" so it stated that people could be wrong, but the meaning was clear. Draco's eyes narrowed. He should be in Slytherin. He wanted to be in Slytherin. But others thought "Anywhere but Slytherin..." and the Hat accommodated them the best it could.

Did the Hat regret that? Or did it regret putting anyone into Slytherin?

"Smith, Zacharias" spent a slow minute under the Hat's brim before winding up, surprisingly, in Hufflepuff. Draco scanned the crowd for wrongly sorted students, looking to find those who should have been in Slytherin. But he couldn't think of any. Vincent and Gregory were saying something and his eyes settled past them, onto Pansy Parkinson. Could he get rid of her? Should he? He glanced around the Hall, again. Mike from Hufflepuff had potential...he thought about the problem.

Draco realized he couldn't solve it. Nobody wanted to be in Slytherin after last year.

"Weasley, Ginevra" was sorted into Gryffindor to the cheers of her rambunctious siblings. Apparently she was the final student because the Headmistress was getting ready to speak.

Draco realized he could solve another problem and stood up. At first, only nearby students looked at him as he took a deep breath. He made no motion to draw attention to himself, other than standing up, and hoped that it would be enough.

"Mr. Malfoy?" Headmistress McGonagall's voice sounded … mild.

"The Hat said it made mistakes. We should let students who think the Hat got it wrong sort again." This set off loud conversations. Draco could hear the shock and Macnair kicked him hard under the table, hissing "We'll have no House left!"

Draco ignored the pain "It's against tradition, but the Hat practically begged us..."

The Headmistress cut him off. "Very well. Does anyone wish to be Sorted again?"

Silence. Nobody wanted to go first, and Draco couldn't volunteer.

Father's training allowed him to stand up, to speak in front of others, to draw attention to himself. He'd ignored fear and shame often enough, though he felt it. For others, it must be paralyzing. Draco walked to the stool and picked up the Hat, carefully keeping it below his head at all times, then quickly returned to Slytherin table, stopping in front of Vincent. Draco held out the Hat.

Crabbe shook his head. "I can't. I shouldn't."

Draco slowly raised the Hat, "You'd be happier. Let the Hat sort again." Crabbe gave a short nod and Draco dropped the Hat on his head before Vince changed his mind. Draco had a few steps to get back to his seat. The whispering had started when the Hat cried out "Hufflepuff!"

The Hufflepuff table broke into applause, joined by Gryffindor and Ravenclaw. Fred Weasley shouted "That's the bravest thing I've seen!" and sounded like he meant it. At the Slytherin table only Draco and Gregory clapped. Draco would have to pretend to lose in the near future, he realized.

Vincent moved to the Hufflepuff Table, wiping his face. He passed the stool, still wearing the Hat, and went back to place it but Padma Patil caught up with him and politely held out her hand. Vincent handed it to her, bowing with a small smile. Padma plonked the Hat firmly on her head with no ceremony.

Draco held his breath, hoping. Padma had been his second in command, after all...

"SLYTHERIN!" came the shout, and Draco clapped, whistled and shouted with rest of the table, except for Pansy Parkinson. Padma's twin Parvarti, sat at Gryffindor, mouth agape and clapped slowly.

When Ginevra Weasley stood up the entire Gryffindor table gasped, and she quickly went into Ravenclaw. At that point the Headmistress stood up.

"Miss Weasley, kindly return the Hat to its place." She held up her hand. "The Hat is available for the duration of the Feast and I, for one, am famished." She clapped her hands twice and the food appeared as Ginny unceremoniously dumped the Hat before rushing to Ravenclaw. She sat next to Luna, who had been sitting alone. Draco tore into a roll and ate.

That had worked out surprisingly well. Vincent would be happier with more friends and less pressure. Padma's surprise had probably saved him at least one beating and meant that there were students, good students, who held sympathy. Draco smiled and ate.

The professors, who normally ate with polite small talk, had an animated discussion that he couldn't quite hear. Professor Burbage filled in the Muggle on details. Draco wasn't positive, but thought The Headmistress had told Flitwick and Slughorn to cool it. The new Head of Gryffindor stared at Draco and a few other students, just eating, no conversation. During the meal three more students went under the Hat, each time causing a hush. Fred Weasley or maybe George sauntered forward just before desert before breaking into a smile and jogging back to his seat under a small barrage of buttered dinner rolls.

After finishing off some iced cake Draco went up and grabbed the Hat, again keeping it low to signal that he wasn't going to put it on. He walked to the Ravenclaw table, eyes locked firmly on Harry Potter.

Harry tried to wave him off but Draco went past Harry and stopped in front of Hermione.

He'd planned a small speech on his walk over. You are incredibly clever, but not enough to convince me that the Girl who stood up to bullies, Dumbledore, Voldemort and Azkaban is rightly sorted. But as he walked over, he realized it didn't need to be said.

"You'd never brag," Draco explained.

Hermione blushed. Draco raised the Hat slightly and paused, just in case she refused. Draco placed it gently on her head and "GRYFFINDOR" rang out instantly with enough force to shove Draco backwards.

The hall exploded into applause and Hermione stood up, as boys patted her arm and girls pulled her into hugs. Draco took the Hat off her head and walked back onto the podium. As he sat down he mumbled "Let's see Ravenclaw win the House Cup now," to nobody in particular.

Harry Potter stood up from the middle of the Ravenclaw. "I promised the Hat I'd never wear it again," which sparked murmuring in the hall and a full-blown five hour debate in the Ravenclaw commons room later that night. "But given it's pronouncement, I'd like to alternate between Ravenclaw and Slytherin."

"Of course you would, Mr. Potter," said the Headmistress. She motioned for him to change seats as the students laughed and a few snaps echoed around the hall. "Anyone else?

Colin Creevey switched to Slytherin, which concluded Hogwart's first Re-sorting.

Author's Confession - I originally wrote these early chapters as a mood piece, and now consider them a prologue. Since I've gotten good response and I'm enjoying writing this, I'm continuing and play to write out a full year. I'll probably have to take some breaks for that.

For the extended story I've got a good plot, mostly consistent. But I see gaps I can't easily fill. I might be able to do it, but it would make the story worse. I'd be adding epicycles, I fear.

My options are to delay until I can bulletproof it or just enjoy the story. Since I stop writing when considering the parts that give me trouble, I've decided to just keep my momentum and hope that I'll spot a solution without agonizing, and accept that there may be some handwaving if I fail. (I find ideas arrive easiest when I don't force them, a theme played out in Draco's daydreaming above, which I wrote weeks ago).

If, at the end of the story you say "But... but... but...", know that I am well aware of several issues and probably missed more, and I wish I could do better.

This is a complex plot, but it's entertainment (hopefully) and writing practice. Constructing a perfect puzzle isn't my motivation. Also, I believe the world is an ambiguous place. So questions like "Is Hermione an Occlumens" (on the train scene) may not be answered early (or ever).

("Such is Realism.")

In most cases I have answers to those questions in mind when I write the scene (I did for that particular example). Sometimes I flub it, though. I will show scenes without Draco to clear things up more (after the prologue), but not every question will be answered. After answering that particular question I decided that I'm going to, in general, let the work speak for itself except for the cases where I realize that I've fallen to the Illusion of Transparency, then I'll answer and revise (or if I've made an easily correctable blunder). I'm not going to defend the decisions in real time, in part because it gives away too much, and it's just not practical.

If you treat this story as a perfect puzzle, at the end you may discover pieces missing. Or poor connections.

I hope you enjoy the picture, though.

I'd like to put a puzzle in, and there will be puzzles, but that's not in any way my primary goal.

Consider this fair warning.

Chapter 9: Known Unknowns

Harry knocked on the door. Gregory cracked it open, glanced at him, then opened the door just wide enough for Harry to slip through.

The room, off the hallway between the entrance to Slytherin House and the commons, felt spacious. Not as large as Harry's trunk, but almost as large as the room his trunk sat in last year, with the rest of the Ravenclaw first year boys. There were three relatively spartan beds, one along the far wall and one each on the left and right. To the right of the far bed Draco sat at his desk, back to the door, writing furiously. Stairs leading down into a small pool of water to the bed's left. Harry wondered if it connected to the pond he passed on the way in.

Gregory walked over to his desk and half-leaned against, half sat on his hands. After a few final notes, Draco firmly shut the small black book, and gently pushed it against the black lacquered cane resting in the crack between desk and wall.

"Hello Harry," Draco said as he stood up. "Sorry, eventful evening."

Harry nodded towards the pool. The torches (torches! Finally!) on the wall provided ample light to play across the small waves that lapped against the top stair, but never seemed to escape past it. "Aren't you worried something may come out of the water?"

"Not really," Draco said. "Alceriato!" The water bubbled noisily, but still never spilled out of the pool. Even inches away from the edge the floor stood bone dry. "It's uncomfortably warm even for a magician. A merman, well..." he shrugged. "Tepidius!" The bubbling faded as the enchantment ended. "In any case it's also an escape route."

Gregory angled his head towards the door, an inquiring look. Draco ignored it and sprawled out on his bed and stared up at the ceiling. "What say you, Gregory? Should we offer Crabbe's bunk to Potter?"

"I don't know, I'd have to think about it. You snore, Potter?"

Draco's tone had been playful, but experience left Gregory no doubt as to the intent. Draco wanted Gregory's opinion, he had doubts.

"I suppose there are upsides," Gregory said noncommittally. Gregory thought that it would be exciting to have Harry Potter for a room-mate, and possibly useful. But Gregory had seen, second hand, the toll that Harry's friendship had put on Draco.

"I didn't mean to impose. In Ravenclaw each year has a room," said Harry.

"Oh, you know very well that's how it works here, too, Potter." Draco waved his hands towards the commons area. "Gregory and I will be summarily booted back there in a week or two, no doubt. So it doesn't cost me anything to be make the offer." Gregory chuckled.

Harry sat down on what he now considered his bed. "Was the duel that important?"

Draco sat up and looked at him, then shoved his back against the wall and drew his feet up against his chest. "That? Not really, which is why I could concede so quickly. That was but a symptom of the reduced status of House Malfoy."

"Then why Strategema with Ethan," Harry asked. Seeing puzzled looks, he explained. "From a Muggle show. A master player frustrates another master by making inferior moves during their game. He ignores superior moves to play for the draw. Which infuriates his opponent."

Draco shook his head. "Nothing so clever. The Duel gave me an opening. A chance to confirm that people could trust me. Could back me, without appearing weak." Draco rested his knees on his chin. "Trust is a rare commodity, here. Ethan handed me a bottle full of it and I decided how to play it, without considering him. And you know the worst part? I'd warned myself against that type of mistake earlier today"

"Well, you got to state your case."

Draco turned slightly towards Gregory, who shook his head.

"Nobody will remember that tomorrow. They've probably forgotten already. If we had people reinforcing our position, restating it..." Gregory trailed off. Potter could figure it out.

Draco sighed. "Every strength has a corresponding weakness."

Harry interrupted. "And vice versa, like using truth serum to your benefit, Draco. That was a good idea."

Draco bit his lip. "Thinking logically helps you, but blinds you to how others think. You can work it out, but it takes time. I'm wondering if it's blinding me, too." He pulled his knees closer.

Harry Potter had seen Draco in a variety of moods before, but morose was new experience.

"I suppose it does. No, I know it does. Its one of those cases where I want to believe people will work things out, despite all the evidence I have from last year. But I have a friend with a masterful understanding of human nature."

Draco snorted. "He's talking about you, Gregory."

"Obviously."

From the noise in the common room it sounded like the prefect had ordered the first years up to their room, the room that Draco had never set foot in all last year.

"Is it really that bad, Draco?"

"I don't know. Imagine how Robert feels, knowing Ethan didn't answer quickly. I had to resign, right away, before he answered. That doesn't even get into Ethan and Sara. I should have never made that accusation." Draco shuffled over to his dresser and started to put away his cloak, to prepare his bed. "And the part that I never considered, was how much I'd been lying to myself. That shook me."

"People lie to themselves all the time, Draco" said Harry.

"Not consciously," said Gregory. "The … awareness of it, that's novel. We could see it, we all saw Draco trying to answer and not being able to." Harry Potter had never seen this side of Gregory (or Vincent, he remembered) and realized that of course Draco Malfoy shared an easy camaraderie with his friends. With a shock Harry Potter remembered Gregory's long pause under the Sorting Hat. At the time, he'd naturally assumed the choice was between Hufflepuff and Slytherin. Now Ravenclaw seemed likely. Lord Malfoy dare not share his secrets with fools, nor would he want fools helping his children.

Gregory's public silence showed that he understood his role. And nothing more.

Harry Potter stood in a room with Draco's consigliere. One of them, anyway. The memory of Lucius with the Elder Goyle and Crabbe, their unspoken coordination, flash to mind. That kind of trust required years. Perhaps generations.

Harry reconsidered if living with Draco would be a good idea, and tried to remember exactly how he'd been invited. Just how detailed a message could they exchange under my nose?

Draco sighed. "Every. Single. Witch. Has probably heard about this by now."

Harry suspected some heard it hours ago. "I should, uh, go get my trunk. I'll be back in a bit."

"Do you need any help?" Gregory and Draco asked simultaneously.

"No, I'm fine." Harry stopped at the door. "Well, there's one thing, at least. I think Salazar Slytherin would approve of this tradition. Who knows? Those duels may date back to Slytherin himself."

"What makes you say that?" Gregory asked, while Draco said "Not that I've heard of."

Harry definitely saw them exchange a look that had meaning he couldn't read.

"Maybe I should find another place to stay," said Harry. "I mean, I think I'd be intruding."

"No, I think you should stay, Potter," said Draco. "But if you do we can't go tip-toeing around like this. I've kept your secrets mostly, from Vincent and Gregory. But if you move in we don't exclude Gregory. You'd be here with both of us. Everything I'm in. I've told him my side already, but … we built up our relation by sharing secrets. This won't work if we all have to spend minutes thinking about what to say."

Harry turned to Gregory. "So, when you said there were upsides..."

"Better to have you inside pissing out, Potter. I live with Draco in any case, I'd like to understand how you spin him around. And since we're all working to save the House" – now Harry shot Draco a look, one that Gregory read easily as 'I suppose fair's fair, but still...' – "it will make all our lives easier."

"So, to confirm, the two of you are inviting me to live here?"

"Until such time as we get booted back to the 2nd year floor," said Gregory, and thrust out his hand.

Harry shook it. "I've got to get my stuff." Gregory held firm.

"So, what did you mean, about Salazar?" asked Gregory, releasing the hand. "What do you know about Slytherin that we don't?"

Harry Potter stood there, thinking.

But he wasn't the only one.

Harry Potter thought faster than most students, faster than most adults even, and he thought faster (and in some ways, deeper) than Draco Malfoy. But he didn't think orders of magnitude faster. Harry Potter quickly considered the implications of revealing his secret to Gregory, whom he didn't know well, and to Draco, who would realize the implication eventually.

But most of Harry Potter's legendary speed came from the fact that he thought ahead. Harry planned for routine trouble and spent time considering trouble most people wouldn't think about. From Harry's point of view, being surprised at his speed of thought was about as useful as being surprised that a Grandmaster could defeat dozens of players simultaneously with almost no effort.

While the Master's opponents stared at the chessboard at move 10, the Grandmaster recognized this game and knew the best move for each response. Grandmasters, as part of their journey, literally wrote books about standard positions. Not only did a Master (of any endeavour) think more clearly and deeply than a novice, in most cases he didn't have to think at all. Certainly not against lesser players. Becoming world class meant outpreparing most opponent, and only out-thinking the truly worthy. Harry Potter's thought ahead about battles, gambits to get or hide information, reacting in the face of disasters. He'd trained himself how to think.

In a novel situation Harry Potter could find a great move, a clever move. But he hadn't prepared one for this.

Harry Potter had wandered into a game half played because he'd tried to cheer up Draco without thinking about it and because he'd been so struck by the symmetry of Draco's Duel and his own experiences (in all respects except for the stakes) that he'd just blurted out his cheerful message. So, for the first time in several days, Harry Potter analyzed a novel position – whether to tell Draco and Gregory.

Harry Potter understood his mistake in making the offhand comment as soon as Gregory asked the question. So, he'd started to think a few seconds before Draco did. But he wasted those few seconds hoping that in in a few years he'd move past these simple mistakes to make more interesting and complex mistakes. And deciding that he didn't fault himself for having tried to cheer up Draco. So, once again, Harry Potter had jumped the starters gun when out-plotting those around him.

But Draco didn't have to think, just remember. A Green-and-Silver lettered day from last year sprang instantly to mind. Draco recognized a mate in one. His only decision: speak or stay silent.

On a normal day Draco Malfoy would have stayed silent. Silence, perhaps masked by meaningless chatter, was usually the prudent course. Silence revealed little. But today Draco felt ambushed by fate and, as so often happens, a player who just blundered away one piece often stops thinking and plays the next obvious move. Or is so relieved to spot a potentially good move that they play first, analyze later (if at all).

But mostly Draco felt annoyed that Harry lacked the courtesy to keep up small talk or try to deflect the conversation while he thought. That insult, more than any calculation, led Draco's revelation.

"Potter's the Heir of Slytherin, Gregory." Gregory's eyes bugged out, then narrowed. Harry Potter turned, took out his wand and cast several wards on the door, then sat on what all three boys now considered his bed.

"I'm not the Heir. But I am Parselmouth. Draco discovered it actually. It's not the sort of thing I'd tell anyone, even Draco. That's why I was thinking. It's not that I don't trust you to keep my secrets. But a lot of people would react ... poorly if I told them. Anyway, Draco was around when it happened. To me it just sounded like English. But Draco couldn't understand it and I'd never even heard of a Parselmouth."

Gregory, more so than either of the other two boys in the room, was in a totally unexpected situation, so it was Draco who interrupted.

"That doesn't really clear it up."

"You can't lie in Parseltongue. It's not quite the same as the serum, I think. It's like two drops, but you can stay silent. But if you speak, you say the truth."

"And what happens if you say something that you don't know is a lie? Do you state the correct information?"

"I don't know, Draco. I don't think so. Almost certainly not" If Parseltongue revealed truths unknown to the speaker, Voldemort would have certainly discovered he had an infallible Oracle. Harry felt practically certain that Parseltongue, like Veritaserum, relied on the subject's state of mind. He'd decided this as Draco walked to his desk and took out a scroll.

"Let's experiment. I don't suppose you know many spells about repairing garments? No? Well, I'll tell you about three of them, one of which is incorrect, and then you say it in Parseltongue … if one of the descriptions changes, then we'll know."

Harry considered the experimental protocols, even though he considered it a forgone conclusion. "If Gregory knows which one is a lie then he shouldn't be visible to me, Draco. I might be able to get a clue from that. It's called the Clever Hans effect..." Harry Potter went on to describe correct experimental protocols at some length, being sure to clarify points for Gregory that Draco already knew.

The experiment proved it. You couldn't knowingly lie in Parseltongue. Harry confirmed that he said "There is a 2/3rd probability that this spell works as follows," because of the information he knew. Once Draco revealed that Percaxia actually cleaned, folded and pressed clothes (and did not fix frayed hems, as he'd written down), then Harry could no longer describe it as a twice likely as not clothess mending sspell, which he'd been able to do earlier and caveats disappeared for the other two descriptions.

Later that night, staring up at the ceiling as Harry and Gregory slept, Draco mentally berated himself. He reviewed that day's mistakes, how the cascading failures piled up. He'd done well, in many regards. He'd seized opportunities and forged ahead. But … but …. Draco couldn't sleep, and rather than toss and turn and fight his insomnia he put his time to use and reviewed the day. He mentally made notes.

Some mistakes he'd only noticed later in the clarity of the night, to the sound of Gregory's snoring.

Draco Malfoy understood his biggest mistake hours earlier. In fact, only several heartbeats after revealing Potter's secret Draco realized the enormity of his mistake. Years later, after he had a more adult control over his emotions, that mistake would be the one that woke him up at night – Revealing his understanding instead of saying silent and thinking things through first.

Like Potter had been trying to do.

The slim comfort Draco took was that he'd at least carried on his conversation as if nothing had happened. He'd avoided the exact same mistake Potter had been making. He hadn't stayed silent (or worse, gasped dramatically) to reveal his thoughts. He'd quickly changed the subject, and changed it well.

He'd offered Harry an experiment.

Draco had no idea if it distracted Harry. Probably not, but Professor Quirrell taught when your only hope is slim you still take it. Draco had no illusions. Harry Potter was neither God nor Monster; legends had already grown around him but Potter wasn't omniscient, just infuriatingly clever. And, like Draco, Harry's youth left him prone to mistakes.

Draco wondered if he underestimated Potter (Harry complained about that often enough). But he'd sometimes overestimated Potter.

More so than anyone else (that he knew), Draco Malfoy had observed Potter up close, had seen his thought processes. He'd seen Harry's powers, magical and non. He'd tried, to the best of his ability, to sort truth from fiction about Harry Potter. Months ago, his intuition told him that Harry Potter defeated Voldemort. He had no evidence. He could think of no experiment. Draco used the old ways of plotting: he assembled facts, gathered information, and thought. He reviewed them again and again that night.

* Harry's Patronus was brilliant and blinding.

* His knowledge of that spell was profound. He'd taught Draco; He'd known Draco could learn it, a fact that surprised Draco and would stun most Slytherins.

* Harry wouldn't reveal his Patronus directly. It contained a secret Potter made an effort to keep hidden.

* According to everyone, Harry Potter terrified a Dementor at Hermione's trial.

* … without even summoning a Patronus.

* Granger's death drove Potter relentlessly.

* He clearly cared for her deeply; more than Draco, possibly more than anyone else.

* Hermione Granger came back from the dead at the same time that Voldemort - her presumed killer - died.

* Hermione Granger could destroy Dementors. She'd destroyed them all, at Azkaban.

Draco had listed those clues over the summer. These facts marked Harry Potter, his friend and rival, as the sort of person who would always outshine him. But also as the boy who avenged Father's death.

He couldn't prove it. He'd probably never have proof. Harry, despite his boyish blunders, would never reveal the fact to anyone he was not completely sure of.

Draco agonized countless hours, wondering if Potter could have prevented Father's death, could have been more clever. Draco didn't know, been afraid to ask. Been afraid of how he might act. Since Draco couldn't trust his own reaction to the news he could hardly blame Harry for being unsure. Harry would never tell him. For friendship, perhaps, but for his own reasons.

Draco knew all of this. He'd pieced it together over the summer, along with his understanding that Father knew he was going to his death that June night.

Draco glanced at the cane on his desk, silver snake head placed so Draco could see it from his bed. The cane Father carried constantly, the Sigil of House Malfoy handed down across centuries. Draco had unlocked some of its secrets, his diary had revealed others. His other birthright.

The cane Draco discovered that night leaning by Father's chair.

A sign, sure as any letter, that Father suspected. His farewell to Draco. Perhaps he'd always left it at home, years ago, when he dealt with Voldemort. Perhaps he feared Voldemort might not restrain himself, might challenge his power against the weight of House Malfoy. Perhaps he could not conceal it, dare not risk anyone spotting it. How often had he left it there? Just in case... so his beloved Narcissa could pass it down to his infant son. Or maybe he'd discovered some dread secret and went knowingly this one time, to protect Draco. Draco didn't know. The game of subtleties had limits. He'd lost the summer wondering.

Could Potter have saved Father? In that regard, Draco felt comforted by his months of reflection. It seemed unlikely. Even if Potter had been there with the Death Eaters, it would be ludicrous to assume he could deal with them and Voldemort. Six hours ago Draco Malfoy trusted Harry Potter, mostly. If he'd been under Veritaserum Draco Malfoy would feel compelled to use a heavily footnoted definition of 'trust' that would cement his reputation for deviousness, terrify Hufflepuffs, and make Potter proud over the sheer precision and deep implications.

Three hours after midnight on the first day of school, Draco Malfoy lay awake agonizing over the new fact (not proven, but probable) he'd added to his list.

Harry Potter chatted with Voldemort before he killed him.

Now, with the moonlight's reflection bathing the commandeered room in a silvery glow, Draco's list of facts about Harry Potter looked alarming.

Author's Note - This ends the prologue.

Chapter 11: Defence and Offence, Pt 2

Asking someone for a favor can form a powerful bond.

- Lucius Malfoy

Draco slept through lunch and the first half of History of Magic. Cutting class was a non-problem, students routinely answered roll call for each other. As long as you didn't say 'present' twice in a row, Professor Binns never noticed. Given his full load Draco had already considered ditching History of Magic anyway for the full year. Draco respected history and its lessons; but, Binns was worthless. He could probably pass all the final right now and use the extra time to study Runes. He didn't need to waste hours each week listening to Binns drone on and on about Goblin Revolutions. He could sleep, like the other students, but it wasn't nearly as comfortable as his bed.

(Only Binns could make Goblin Revolutions boring. History tutoring started even before magical tutoring at Malfoy mansion. Draco's bedtime stories, like all great fables, taught lessons.)

Stretching awake, Draco pulled out his schedule.

3pm – Intermediate Muggle Studies (All Houses). Professor Asimov. (New Annex).

Draco blinked. Intermediate? He hadn't signed up for intermediate. Had Harry adjusted his schedule? He'd asked Harry, on the train, about tutoring. Draco walked through the dungeons, navigating automatically. Left - past the picture of Mad Witch Matilda - laughing as she burned in a bonfire. She'd enjoyed it so much Muggles 'caught' her dozens of times in the 1500s. Up the Squeaking Stairs, air no longer cool as Draco arrived in the main levels. He headed for the Great Hall, taking the long way instead of risking a shortcut. Headmistress had told them directions to the Annex, from the Great Hall.

The schedule allowed plenty of time between classes, especially for the first week of school as students discovered changes over the summer. Walls stood in the middle of hallways, pits and spring-loaded traps would launch you onto a balcony. Last December a shimmering gateway - a bright orange oval - had appeared in the wall underneath Mad Matilda. Anyone stepping into it would step out of another gate, identical to the first but blue, a mere minute from Potions. Slytherins grumbled bitterly when it disappeared a few days later, it had cut out a good ten minutes of walking. Each way.

Draco came to the Great Hallway and walked down the new set of short, black stairs, wide enough for only a single person. Fortunately a second set crossed over the first, enchanted so that students could only go up. The grooves on each stair, coupled with the graceful curve of the vertical side reminded students of the the black Elbonian ridgeback dragon, and the name had stuck.

Draco stepped off the Ridgeback and turned left, hearing the matching giggles. He pulled out his wand and quickly aimed it at Flora and Hestia Carrow. Hestia, straight hair in a ponytail, square glasses that actually looked quite fetching, served in Diggory's army last year but Flora had finished her O.W.L.S. He aimed at Hestia on instinct and stepped back, to get some distance.

"Do we scare you, Malfoy?" Flora swished her wand with a flick of the wrist left right left right making little tsk tsk cutting noises in the air. All the Carrow girls were short, but she stood taller than Draco, probably would for the full year. Hestia's wand never wavered off him.

Draco breathed deeply while speaking. "No, although I wonder where your sister has wandered off to. A falling out?" Draco's eyes never left Flora, but he shifted his head slightly to adjust his peripheral vision. Draco didn't see anyone else. He'd been early, but other students should be following in a few minutes.

"Going to study the ikky Muggles, Drakey?" That would sound silly if Flora said it, Hestia pulled it off.

"No, I'm just Steleus!" Draco shouted the hex out and threw himself to the right to avoid Flora's stupefy, cast almost at the same time. Hestia handily blocked his curse but Flora doubled over sneezing. Hestia's Stupefy went wide and Draco flipendo'd Flora to the ground, going for the easy hit and removing her from the fight before she recovered. Flora tumbled backwards, still sneezing and Draco ran left (so his right hand wasn't blocked by his own torso). He blocked Hestia's drill breaking hex and tried his own Expelliarmus when he heard a screeched Ventus Tria. Draco dived for the floor as the jet of wind rushed over his back, but still got thrown sideways by the blast. He hit the ground rolling, hard slippery cobblestones digging into his shoulder blades and the world was upside-down when he spotted Sheila, the cow. Draco kept rolling then slapped the ground with his left arm to stop, his right arm pointed back

"Tarantallegra!"

Draco didn't wait, waiting got you hit, he'd already shoved both arms under him and he was scrabbling forward, crawling as he climbed into a run. Sheila went down in a tangled mass of her own two legs, but Hestia was behind him. Draco juked and heard several jinxes but didn't see anything. He glanced over his shoulder and she was aiming and shouting. Just shouting, not actually casting. Waiting for a good shot. Draco spun around, stumbling, and fired off a Maledictonum, which just caused stuttering and twitching and was more prank than hex, since it only affected normal speech and not spells. But it sounded dangerous and he'd won three fights by firing off random spells and having his targets dodge wildly in fear. Last November, Hannah Abbot jumped into the lake to avoid Draco's magical hair grooming. Hestia stood her ground, either recognizing the spell or seeing that he'd fire wide, and her carefully aimed Colloshoo hit Draco squarely in the chest. With his feet stuck to the ground Draco's momentum bent him awkwardly the waist and he felt the blinding light as his head impacted the cobblestone.

Then darkness.

"Ennervate!"

Anxious faces looked down at Draco. Students milled past them, peered in, giggling, gasping, laughing and shouting. A hand was reaching down to help him up and Draco focused on it, grabbed it. As he started to pull himself up he realized he'd been kicked hard in the sides and pain shot through him. He couldn't pull himself up and the hand easily pulled him to his feet, steadied him, and Draco finally looked at the face.

"Thank you, Robert," Draco gasped. His left knee almost gave out and Susan Bones slipped herself into his side as Robert cast more spells.

"Episkey. You still look terrible," Robert said. "Your face is worse. You should go see Pomfrey."

"I'll be fine. I've already missed one class today." Draco looked around and saw that, apart from Robert Jugson, the huddle had been Susan, Padma, Neville and a particularly worried Vincent. Draco cocked his head. Vincent understood, but the throbbing pain Draco felt made him think it would have been better to ask.

"They were kicking you pretty hard," said Vincent, "something might be broken. We were heading back from Muggle Studies but they ran off once Robert saw them." Vincent didn't need state the obvious, Gregory had chased after them, to confirm who was involved and enact any retribution.

"It was the Carrows."

"I saw at least four people around you, but only one kicking." said Padma. There was disagreement, Neville thought it was just three. Robert offered that Shelia had gotten a few boots in. Draco put a bit of weight on his knee. He could walk, gingerly. Vincent latched on to the side opposite Susan.

"Thanks for getting them off me. That could have turned ugly." The general opinion was that it had gotten ugly. Robert mumbled a goodbye and walked off. By now there wasn't much of a crowd going past out of class, but a small trickle of older students were descending the Ridgeback while Draco, supported by Susan and Vincent, made the slow walk down the hall. Draco fumbled for his wand and pointed it to his sides and mumbled Te Manawa. The pain eased. Draco shifted the wand towards his face and cast Tango Karawarawa. He didn't have a mirror so he cast it again until Vincent nodded.

Malfoys collected spells that improved your appearance.

After being lowered (gently) into a seat in the back row Draco numbed his knee, which he hadn't dare do while walking. A few other glamours improved his appearance and fixed his clothing. Most students would hear the gossip, but at least Draco didn't look like someone who lost a fight.

The Professor spoke into a device that apparently functioned like a Sonorus spell. He also had sheets of paper.

"Good afternoon, class. I am Professor Asimov. As you may know, I've recently been hired to teach at Hogwarts. Forgive me for not knowing your names, although I have a class list here with pictures. Since I am a squib, I ask that you keep your actual appearance and not take this opportunity to prank the new teacher. We will focus on Muggle society trends instead of simple facts. However, since your prior classes were hogwash I'll summarize the facts, at least for the English Speaking Muggle world. As we progress I'll be interested to hear what topics you'd like to cover, and we will move towards a dialogue. Today's topic will be a brief history of the Industrial Revolution, and the impact on the Muggle beliefs in magic..."

At the end of the lecture Draco waited for the room to clear before removing the anesthetic spell on his knee. He used the chair's hand-rests to push himself up, then extended his left leg to the ground. It held.

"Why don't you use magical healing?" Professor Asimov, walking down the aisle towards Draco.

"Healing spells require raw power. I'll have to be older before I have it. They don't even start theory for a few years." Draco started out the door and the Professor walked with him.

"You are younger than your classmates, but not a Muggle born, so why are you in my class … Draco?" The professor had rifled through the sheets and found a picture of Draco. He'd done that several times to call on students during the class.

"I figured you'd know, sir." Draco moved slower than strictly necessary, but it made his walk seem less like a hobble.

"The Headmistress didn't say, and you needn't be so formal, Draco."

"Of course. Although if you don't mind some advice, you are too informal in lectures. You should stick to Mister So-and-so and Miss whoever." Draco paused and thought. "Now that I think about it, I'm not sure if that's a national difference or a Muggle/Wizarding difference. Is there a word for that?"

"Not that I'm aware of. My apologies, then Mr. Malfoy."

"None required, as I knew it was an innocent mistake. But some students don't."

"And that must be why you were in my class." The Professor stopped at a small doorway. Draco realized it was a Muggle door you might see in a home, gaudily painted, two small squares inlaid, one atop the other. "This is my office. Do you have a few moments?"

Draco followed Professor Asimov in. The room was lined with shelves, books stacked a dozen high on the desk, leaving only enough free space for a manual typewriter, some paper, and several legal pads. Draco squeezed past the visitor chair to look at the closest shelf.

"You wrote all of these?" All the books said "Asimov" or "Isaac Asimov." Many titles read as gibberish but some were science books. There must be hundreds of books, all four rows were written by his Professor. Draco found a title and picked it out.

"Mostly just that bookcase. I'm afraid that book isn't what you hope, Draco." Draco put Young Witches and Wizards back on the shelf and continued browsing.

"Just Muggle fiction, I'm afraid. The majority of my books are fiction, although I wrote general interest pieces on current scientific knowledge. Current for the time, I suppose." Draco spotted a picture on the back of one book's outer paper wrapper, which showed the Professor as a much older man, gray hair, skin dropping, but still the same glasses and general look. Draco judged the man in the picture to be roughly 100, firmly middle aged. He put the book back.

"So, they made you younger."

"I imagine I'd be dead in a few years if not. I'm grateful that Headmistress McGonagall offered me this position. Anyway, I wanted to ask you something, Draco."

"Of course, Professor Asimov." Draco kept browsing. His training told him to sit, he could hear his tutors screaming. But Harry Potter had clearly hand-picked this Muggle and Draco had heard you can never have too many books often enough. Such a prolific author and scientific expert deserved study. Anyway, expressing interest in a Ravenclaw's writing surely exemplified politeness. Probably. For Muggles, too. Maybe.

"Are you OK? I mean, I gathered from the other students that you'd been in a fight with several older students, and given what you told me about raw magical talent...well." Isaac Asimov watched the young boy examining the books stop and consider. He stood almost straight, although his weight was obviously on one leg. He'd spoken well, partially due to how refined British English sounds to an American ear, but the boy had an aristocrat's bearing.

"I am OK, in the sense that you just offered to help and I am declining. I surely don't know how things like this are handled … outside. But you damage us both if you publicly interfere. But, I thank you for the offer, Professor Asimov." Once Draco started speaking he'd gone back to browsing books titles. They may reveal something, but he only understood a fraction of them.

"Please, call me Isaac. And I don't understand how you can let them do that, and others can stand by, it's just not natural."

At this Draco sat. "To answer your question, first of all that happened to be a reasonably fair fight. Some magic is about raw age, but not most of it. As to your other question, I'll answer, but I need to know how much you understand. What did they tell you about us and about the relationship between our worlds? About last year?"

"Well, Magic was real. I'd seen a little bit, here and there, as a child. A talking cat scolded me for almost getting run over on 5th Avenue, when I was, oh, around eight years old. I'd see a doorway nobody else could see. Things like that. So, for a while I'd believed in magic, but never found any evidence, so I just dismissed it as being young and foolish..."

Draco sighed internally. Most people, when asked a question, told a personal story instead of giving an answer. Ninety percent of politics involved feigning interest and Draco kept nodding. But to listen to someone who'd written literal bookshelves of relevant knowledge spout on ….

("That must have been hard on you," said Draco) ...was particularly frustrating.

"I don't know, my experience nourished my sense of wonder, made me question those around me. It may have kept me from following those foolish beliefs that captured so many of my friends, although my father helped. They didn't believe my stories, why should I believe theirs? And I see those like me, squibs, born into your world and they seem bitter. Better to glimpse these visions than stare at them too long. You don't risk staring at the sun, not before you have the right tools. Fortunately we only have one, not six."

"What?" Draco didn't know exactly what would happen if more suns appeared in the sky. Maybe you could deal with a second. OK, but hot. More sounded dangerous, especially if there was a water failure, and there would probably be a panic...

"Sorry. Just a phrase. Anyway, I was shocked to find out I hadn't been imagining it. They offered youth and health for teaching, and of course I jumped. Even without that I'd have done it, just to learn. I know about the Statute of Secrecy, of course. I'm sworn to keep that. Not that I'll be allowed to leave the campus for several years, until things get settled."

"You aren't being coerced? Did you actually swear to any spell? Or just give your word?" Draco asked.

"I haven't had any magic done to me, apart from the healing." Professor Asimov seemed confident.

Not that you know. But even a Muggle would recognize an Unbreakable Vow as magic.

"And how we view your world?" Draco asked.

"I know that most of you don't really give it much thought, but those who do don't think well of us."

"As you said: facts first, then implications. So, the facts. They told you the polite version. For the other houses you basically don't exist, or are maybe some exotic rarity. For my house, Slytherins, Muggles are sub-humans, not even worthy of pity. How Muggles might treat people of different colour a century ago, as Harry Potter explained it to me."

Professor Asimov interrupted, "Harry who?" Draco didn't pause, but just filed the information away. Either Harry is busy, or worried about some appearance of impropriety. He'd think about it later.

"Oh, just my room-mate. Raised by Muggles. I haven't examined his books closely but I suspect he owns several of your books. I'm surprised he hasn't asked to talk to you. But anyway, you heard about last year? About the murders? Yes, then the fallout also affected Slytherin. Most victims and Voldemort, the murderer, were Slytherins. Voldemort preached hatred of Muggles. He's dead, but still has followers."

"So … this is not simple bullying then."

"No. I insist you do not get involved, for your own safety. I know it must sound odd, to hear this from a child." Draco looked abashed, but sounded firm. "But I suspect you'd get the same advice from the Headmistress or teachers. Stick to teaching your lessons, and learning about us. Let the situation cool. Even your presence is provocation enough, to some. I got ambushed by three witches because they fear me. They fear what you represent, but they don't fear you personally. I suspect that's why you can't leave Hogwart's. The wards aren't perfect, but if you wandered without protection..."

"Thank you for the advice, Mr. Malfoy." Professor Asimov sounded unconvinced, but solemn.

"Of course, Professor ... Isaac. If you don't mind, I'd like to continue these chats. I believe we can both learn quite a lot. I know that I have so many questions."

Author's Note – When I came up with DMPOR and added a Muggle professor of Muggle Studies, I decided to only consider people listed on the Wikipedia Category "Muggles who Died in 1992." I kept looking after I saw Isaac Asimov's name (it felt silly to give up without even finishing the As) but he really is the perfect choice and after I got halfway through the alphabet I finally admitted it.

According to Muggle History he died in April of 1992, which is prior to Harry getting the stone. This is not important to the plot, but it's a nit I choose to ignore.

It has also been pointed out that Gilderoy was a Ravenclaw in canon. Yeah, that's another divergence. So, when I say I'm trying not to diverge from HPMOR, I'm not trying hard, especially on little details. (I am not diverging from Multiple-Hypothesis Testing, at least I don't think so, but I'll let that speak for itself.)

Update #2 - It has been pointed out that Matilda is just Wendelin the Weird, whom I probably vaguely remembered. Oh well.

Chapter 13: Bold Thinking, Pt 1

"Foolish people work hard to appear happy. Work hard to be happy." - Lucius Malfoy

The howler arrived early, well before breakfast. It didn't arrive in the Great Hall, of course. Draco had heard Tanaxu's arrival and groggily opened his eyes in time to see the letter, growing red and about to burst. Draco managed to grab the letter and dive into Harry's trunk before it exploded. Harry slept through it, of course, his Quietus slider was always set to high when he slept. Draco preferred to be able to hear his surroundings, even if that disturbed his sleep from time to time. Still, Gregory only caught a few words, which meant that the rest of Slytherin probably hadn't.

Now, heart pounding, Draco sat at his desk writing.

Mother,

We are family, and if not as close as we should be, still I do not wish to plot against you.

I share your concerns about our future, but money sitting in a vault acts as a general's reserve, and like a reserve it must be used at the proper time. I will cease spending "extravagantly" if you aid my search for Severus Snape and assist my investigations. Father swore Snape joined Voldemort, yet he survives. Besides, I fear you are moping. I know it is not my place, but it would serve you well to get out of the house.

Please, for his memory and our future, assist me.

PS What do you know of my Professors? Which may be allies?

"Well, Don't ogres make soup out of people's bones? That would explain the skinning," said Vincent.

Offense started in thirty minutes and most of the class were still brainstorming theories.

Neville shook his head. "I don't think Ogres sneak up on people like that. If they attacked, everyone would know. I'm thinking it's a Tystnaden."

"Hm. That might work," said Hermione. She still stayed in the regular girl's dorm and Lavander Brown had instantly sought out the most famous Gryffindor's advice, since everyone knew that Hermione had read literally dozens of books. Hermione, intrigued, had spent several days reading through the library to see if she could solve this mystery. Seeing that nobody apart from Neville knew what they were discussing, she explained. "The Tystnaded is a creature that obliviates anyone who sees them. So, you see, it may have actually stumbled on the whole group, killed one of them, and then the rest of them forgot."

"Ooh, what do they look like?" said Colin Creevey. He'd attached himself to the group as had several other students. Any spotting of Hermione Granger and Harry Potter drew a crowd, these days.

"Well, obviously nobody knows," sniffed Hermione. She was used to the crowds, but the fact that the first year kept following her around made her wary. Still, she'd gotten used to it enough that she didn't put as much bite into her words as most girls would have.

"They sound dangerous. Tricky," said Harry. He'd also been attracted to the problem but hadn't had nearly as much free time and hadn't even heard of a Tystnaden until now. "If only the people who see them get obliviated, then would probably want to avoid crowds. Others would see the first people getting confused, they'd get wary. Maybe start casting area-effect hexes. If I were a Tystnaden I don't think I'd attack crowds. I'd pick off lone individuals. But the creature did that, or they think it did. So why would the Aurors separate?" Harry looked visibly shaken and spent several hours over the next day planning how to defeat a Tystnaden. The first trick was to recognize you'd been obliviated, and it would help to precommit to what kind of message you'd leave yourself...

The conversation continued while the first years poured out of the lecture hall and Luna Lovegood, hearing strange and possibly mythical creatures named by several students, chimed in. "It's a Yautja," she said, in an air less distracted than she usually used.

"I've never heard of that," said Draco, who had followed behind her.

"Of course," said Luna sweetly. "They are invisible hunters who only attack the strongest victims. Like Aurors, or adventurers. It's their rite of passage."

"That does kind of fit," said Neville.

"So why aren't more people killed by them," asked Hermione. "I mean, if every one of these creatures has to do this?"

"Oh, they rarely hunt on Earth," said Luna. "It's too far away."

Several students laughed and Harry Potter just snorted while the discussion turned to reasonable options.

In Peverell Hospital, Draco walked around examining security when someone called his name.

"So," said one of the Weasley twins, "he's got you doing it too. Any ideas?" The other one was quickly rolling up a scroll of some sort. Draco thought he saw a map, which made sense. He was still getting a feel for the layout. Security seemed impossibly tight, with Aurors guarding entrances and confiscating anything useful (although they'd let him keep a quill and his journal, to take notes). Draco glanced from one to the other.

"Twins raises a possibility. Have you considered using the two of you, one disguised as someone else? Then removing it for the confusion aspect?"

"Thief's Downfall." They said together. Then they started alternating phrases. "And please / we're experts / First thing we / thought of. We've racked our brains / trying to take advantage / it's hard to see something." One shrugged, slightly ahead of the other turning around. The Aurors watched them carefully. Draco had shown a note from Harry to allow him in (searched, but he could get the benefit of a doubt to bring in items that might normally be confiscated).

"I assume there's an anti-Apparition jinx?"

"Of course," said Fred, or maybe George. A trio of Aurors started to move a patient from his bed into the Healing Room, and Draco heard the splash of the Thief's Downfall.

Draco asked "Do we know if that blocks non-Wizards?"

"Well, I'm not sure," said George or maybe Fred.

They exchanged a look and Fred, Fred?, continued. "We tried to summon the Sorting Hat but it doesn't answer us most of the time."

George, George?, shrugged. "I think it knows when we're actually desperate and testing doesn't count."

"I was actually thinking more of House Elves," Draco said. One of the twins raised an eyebrow and they all huddled together to discuss possible solutions.

In the dungeons near Slytherin.

Harry Potter realized, now that he lived there, that this unused classroom lit with eerie green light didn't belong to the Slytherin dungeons proper. Draco had never let him into the Syltherin Dungeons, the rest of the Slytherins referred to this as the "public" dungeon.

Which made it still convenient to teach lessons to the expanded Bayesian Conspiracy. Draco invited the Silvery Slytherins, so that added Daphne Greengrass and Gregory. (Draco tried to not think of her as Daphne of Greengrass, because he might slip and say it. A Malfoy never insults by accident). Harry Potter had invited Hermione and Neville, for now. For the first two weeks lessons covered material Draco already knew. He'd co-taught, provided examples, translated Muggle concepts into Wizarding terms. But now Draco found himself lost with the rest of the non-Harry Potters.

They'd gotten diverted when Draco stated that the methods didn't help during a fight.

"What do you mean, of course they do" said Harry.

"I'm being imprecise," Draco admitted. "They help at times during a battle, but during lulls. I'm not saying that they are useless. Just limited during an actual battle. Once the spells are flying you don't have time for this."

"The techniques are useful for decision making, and you make decisions all the time during battle."

Draco just cocked his head in question.

"You kind of don't," said Neville. "I mean, you are flying around with Chaotic Leaps, kicking, punching, casting spells, dodging. We spend a lot of time preparing, but during the battle itself we just kind of re-act. I mean, if you imagine a battle where your enemy chats with you for a few hours sure …. but real battles?"

Hermione said "Right. All the decision making is done ahead of time. And it's been really useful, I agree. "

Draco nodded. "Right. I mean, I'm certainly making decisions, but all of these techniques, they cost too much time I just pick something that's good enough. It's not like I'm consciously deciding or weighing trade offs. It feels like I'm not making any decisions at all, during a fight. On the first day, when I got ambushed, it's not like I did anything clever. Either time I got ambushed. I don't feel like I made any decisions, even though I tried. But that's only when the spells fly. Even in a battle, there's lots of time to think about things. Just not then."

Harry considered this for a full minute.

"There's a theory for this, called recognition primed decision making. They interviewed firefighters and soldiers to figure out how they made decisions, and they talked to one fire captain who said he didn't think he'd made a decision in a fire during his entire career. He did, of course, he made lots of decisions. Once, there was a tiny fire in a two-story house. His team goes into the ground floor and uses a muggle Aquamenti to douse the fire, but it doesn't go out. In fact, the fire roars back at them. So the captain orders his men out, and right as they are leaving the floor collapses. It turns out there was a basement and it had been on fire for a long time. The captain attributed getting his men out to his sixth sense."

Harry paused. "But you see, it was really just him subconsciously noticing confusion. Once the interviewer sat down and asked him to explain the situation in detail, explain it to someone who wasn't a fire-fighter, there were all these tiny details he'd noticed. The way the smoke moved, the way the fire reacted. The captain knew it didn't add up, so he did the prudent thing and retreated. Just in time."

"Yes, but the only lesson is to be experienced," Draco said. "Other people, even the novice fire fighters didn't notice the problems. You can't teach that. Our battles give us that experience, and we use the techniques outside of battles, afterwards, to clarify our thoughts. We prepare. The preparation makes us strong. It's not that the techniques are useless, not by any means."

Harry held up his hand, and Draco stopped.

"I agree, but I think I can explain this better. We've covered experimentation and falsifiability, but efficiency matters in the real world too. I agree with your general point. Sometimes you have to make snap decisions, and yes, in those cases you can't do everything perfectly. Unlike the 2-4-6 game, sometimes you don't have the time or ability to make a bunch of predictions and get answers. Sometimes you only have a few chances, or even one chance, like the fire-fighter. I think there are some applicable lessons."

"Consider Chocolate Frogs. They come with those Famous Witch and Wizard trading cards, right? Well, they appear to be randomly distributed. I couldn't afford real chocolate frogs, and it would distract us to have them, so I just made a pretend set of trading cards. I'd been saving this for another lesson, but I think it applies. Suppose you want to complete your set of trading cards. If you could predict which card was in which box, you'd just have to buy one box to complete your set, instead of trade. And you only have enough money to buy so many frogs before you run out of money or your parents ground you for eating too much chocolate."

Harry had been mumbling a few words here and there, and finally pulled a pack of Muggle cards from his pouch and set them on the table. "Rather than guess the exact person on each card, we'll just guess if it's a Witch or Wizard. Here, I'll deal a few cards out."

Harry flipped over the top cards of the deck and placed them on the table. Draco got a Wizard, Daphne got a Wizard, Gregory got a Witch, as did Hermione. Neville got a Wizard and then Harry flipped up another card and placed a Wizard in front of himself. Harry picked up the next card and looked at Draco. "Let's play a game, at your turn you guess the gender whoever gets the most cards correct gets an actual Chocolate Frog."

"Witch," said Draco. "We've never seen more than two in a row," he added. Harry flipped over the card and put it down in front of Draco. It was a Wizard.

"Don't feel bad. You made a prediction and you were wrong, but you stated a rule that could be falsified. You performed an experiment. Incidentally, that reminds me of the Better's Oath. We aren't betting, but we are playing a game for stakes, which is similar. I happen to like betting because it forces you to think clearly about how probable something is. Anyway, part of the Better's Oath is 'When I win a bet, I will not shame my opponent, for a betting loser has far more honor than the mass of men who live by loose and idle talk.' So it would be wrong of us to shame Draco, he had an idea, he tested it. He's learned something."

Harry held out the next card, still face down, in front of Daphne. "Witch. I don't know, it just seems like we've had a lot of Wizards." The card was a witch. Harry started to hand it to her, then just put it down and put a pebble on it.

"That way we can still see the pattern. I'll mark the correct cards. Winner still gets a frog. Since we're talking about fast decision making, you have to think fast."

Gregory guessed Wizard correctly, Hermione incorrectly called a Witch, Neville guessed Witch and got one. Harry flipped up a wizard in front of himself without guessing, then pulled out a card for Draco.

"Wizard."

Harry held the card still. "You don't have a theory?" Draco just shrugged so Harry flipped up the card, it was a wizard. They played a few more rounds, faster this time, then Harry set aside the deck and said. "OK, we have a moment to retreat. Now we can apply the theories. So, what do we know. You can see the pattern that's there. Look at what you see."

Hermione started. "There are 30 cards out, and 19 of them are wizards, which seems like yet another bias against Witches. I know, these are famous ones and there are more famous wizards than witches, but it still goes that way."

Draco said "We've had up to five wizards in a row, starting with Neville's fourth card and working around. We've only had three witches in a row."

Gregory had been doing some counting. "After a witch, we had 7 wizards and 4 witches. I'm not sure that means anything."

Neville started to bring up Arithmancy, but Harry cut him off. "The lesson has nothing to do with that. Well, not with Wizarding Arithmancy, math is involved. But I promise it doesn't have anything to do with magical numbers. Well, I suppose it could, but since I don't know much about it it's not my intent."

Harry let them discuss the patterns for four more minutes. "Does anyone have any theories or ideas?"

Nobody did. Actually, Gregory proposed a rather elegant theory, but Neville found a counterexample in the second round. Gregory thought about this and modified his theory, and Harry pointed out that this additional complexity should weigh against him believing his theory, but that didn't mean it was wrong. But nobody else had any ideas.

"OK," said Harry, "Now we're back to an actual battle. I'm going to deal out the rest of the cards. Three left for each person. Draco?"

By this point Draco had given up. The pattern was too complex for him to see. He picked Wizard the next three cards, and was right twice. After another minute, the deck was exhausted and Draco was tied with Neville and Daphne.

"I should have made more cards, a tie was too likely. When I thought of this I figured we'd have fewer people. Anyway, we've got enough information to prove my point. Gregory's theory was proven wrong soon after he amended it, so there's that."

"So, what was it?" asked Neville. "What was the pattern?"

"Oh, it was random. Just like I said it appeared. I made the cards with the right ratios and then shuffled them up before I got here. About 70% of the cards are Wizards and 30% are Witches, which seems to be the actual ratio the Chocolate Frog company uses, because there are more famous Wizards than Witches, Hermione, which may or may not be unfair but that's how it is."

"So, you rigged it," said Gregory. "There's no lesson."

"No, there are lots of lessons. The first lesson is that people are really good at finding patterns where none exist, and then convincing themselves to ignore other evidence. We're trained to see patterns, we see faces in clouds. More importantly the cost for being wrong is usually much much lower than the cost for not seeing a pattern. If you saw a stick and thought it was a snake and jumped up, the worst that would happen is that people would laugh at you. But if you didn't see a snake that was there, you could get killed. So that's why we jump at shadows. Seeing a pattern that isn't there is called Pareidolia, by the way. As for the second lesson. Daphne, why did you bet Wizard, Witch, Wizard for your last three rounds?"

"Well, not knowing it was random, I just tried to make sure that I guessed two wizards to one witch. That was the closest thing we had to a pattern."

Harry nodded and then turned to Neville.

"Same idea. By the last round I had six wizards and only one witch, so I called witch and got it."

"And you, Draco?"

"I didn't see a pattern, so I just called Wizard each time."

"Why wizard?"

"There were more wizards."

"Draco was moderately unlucky, actually. There were more wizards than witches, so when Daphe and Neville actually called Witch one of the final rounds, that should have cost them. If we'd kept playing long enough, Draco would win as long as he kept calling Wizard. If you kept calling Witch one-third of the time, you'd slowly lose out, even though Witches are one-third of the cards. But in the short term, you can get lucky. The funny thing is, if you tell people that the cards are heavily slanted towards Wizards, like Hermione pointed out, people still try to guess Witch every now and then, which is silly. If you don't know the pattern, it may as well be random, so why are you trying to predict something you can't possible know?"

"That still sounds like you cheated for this game," said Daphne.

"Look, imagine Voldemort chasing you. From experience you know that people who go down into the dungeons get away ten times out of one hundred and the people who go into towers survive five times out of one hundred. If you had time to do a full scientific study, you could figure out why or how that was."

"Sadly, Voldemort does not agree to help you, he just wants you dead. But your first goal is to survive Voldemort … or win the game you are playing. So, head to the dungeons. If you have to make a decision right away make the best decision you can with the information you have. If you want to make a prediction, you can tell yourself the hypothesis and what you expect to happen in your head. But make the best bet to survive or win the Chocolate Frog. Like Draco did. In the short term, you could get unlucky, but it's the best you can do, until you come up with a better hypothesis."

"So," said Draco, "You do agree that you have to at least recognize that a situation is weird, then you take your best shot or retreat to figure it out? And that preparation will allow you to make good, even great decisions in most situations, when you don't have time to sort things out."

"I said as much," said Harry. "Look, my methods aren't perfect. They are a tool. They don't guarantee you'll be right they just help you be …. less wrong. The point is to examine your experiences, and use those tools. Sometimes the best you can do is instinct, but instinct is also a trap."

That lead to a long discussion about various modes of thinking, and Harry said that the real issue, which they didn't have time for, was on hypothesis generation, and they'd discuss it at the next meeting. Later that night Draco, sucking the last bits of chocolate from his hand, opened his diary to the final page.

Author's Note – The Better's Oath was formed by Bryan Caplan, the full version can be found at EconLog.

Recognition Primed Decision Making was in fact studied in the 80s, but I have no idea how Harry Potter got that information. We'll assume his father subscribes to journals. My example and many notes are taken from "Sources of Power: How People Make Decisions" by Gary Klein. I had the pleasure of meeting Doctor Klein a decade ago, although we did not discuss his research.

The experiment that Harry performs (guessing cards) is actually published in '96. A. Tversky and W. Edwards (1966). "Information versus reward in binary choice." Journal of Experimental Psychology, 71, 680-683. See also Y. Schul and R. Mayo 2003, "Searching for certainty in an uncertain world." In Journal of Behavioral Decision Making, 16:2, 93-106. (I found a reference to it on E.Y.'s site)

Tversky also collaborated with Daniel Kahneman, whose book "Thinking: Fast and Slow" served as a partial inspiration for the chapter. T:F&S discusses many of the same biases as listed in HPMOR.

Chapter 16: Bold Thinking, Pt 3

'You will rarely be caught in a lie your victim wants to believe. He would rather make the lie come true than expose you." - Lucius Malfoy

"What I'm trying to get at," Harry Potter said to the gathered Bayesian Conspiracy, located in the potions classroom near Slytherin, "is that the fastest course of action is to make the boldest prediction possible, then experiment."

Neville asked "What do you mean by bold?"

"I mean something simple, something powerful. The old theory of planetary motion stated that the Earth stood still and everything else moved around it. But that meant planets sometimes changed directions. That theory worked, but had lots of convoluted answers and math. The newer, bolder theory placed the sun at the center. It made predictions that allowed easier calculations."

"But what if that theory had been wrong?" Daphne asked a lot of clarifying questions, which Harry appreciated. She'd made a great addition to the group for that reason alone. "I mean, that theory was correct and happened to be bold, but what if the right theory was timid?"

"Well, if you make a bold prediction and are wrong, you tend to be wrong quickly," Harry said. "I lost days trying to fine tune a prediction last year, when an hour of work would have told me I was wrong. In the case of an incorrect bold theory, you typically discover a counter example quickly, and then can go back and think. It's not that you'll be right every time, but when you are wrong you'll gain insight into the problem, and hopefully won't waste as much time."

Draco and Gregory headed up the stairs, towards the offence classroom. Draco taught again today, leading the discussion of how Ginevra Weasley's Genies had destroyed Nicholas Martin's Manticore Army and Zacharias Smith's Spectres. First year Generals had been advised to take unused army names and once "Ginny's Genies" had formed the other two stuck with the best alliterations they could think of that could be considered fearsome. Like Draco feared, the battle – such as it was - hadn't been close. He didn't relish talking about it for the next hour and a half. Weasley's army had faked being dead as had Smith's army. But, unlike Zacharis Smith, Ginny had thought ahead and issued a standing order to shoot dead enemies again, 'just to be sure.'

Gregory had insisted on going with Draco. In theory, to protect Draco from another ambush, everyone knew Draco lectured today. In practice ...

"Look," said Gregory, "Montague and Flint are good chasers, Bletchley's a solid keeper, if a bit uninspiring, but I just can't work with Peregrine. I mean, he's a good flyer, better than Vincent even, but I just never know what he's going to do."

"You can hardly expect to build up the same rapport in a few days. Who is the other chaser?" asked Draco.

"I think it's Warrington, but he's rubbish. Won't be good for another year, at least. I just don't know what to do with Derrick. I realize we've only had five days, but he has the strangest ideas about what the beater position entails. Although I suppose it's all up in the air this year, isn't it? Two forty-five minute halves? Who thinks of these things?"

They went up another flight of stairs, in the distance they heard a crash and Peeves shouting. The first years were probably behind them and didn't know the poltergeist's typical ambush points. "Well, Gregory, take some comfort that Vincent is complaining to Hufflepuffs about their other beater, uh …."

"Rickett," Gregory supplied. Right, thought Draco, Anthony Rickett. He tried to visualize Rickett. Tall for his age, but that may just be an early growth spurt. Brown hair, kind of weaselly look. The animal, not the family.

"Anyway, I'm sure that Vincent has spent the last week complaining that Rickett isn't a bad guy, but he's no Gregory Goyle." The walked past a landing, sunlight streamed through a small vertical slit of a window, with a tapestry hanging besides it. Draco stopped and examined it, then spun around.

"That is one ugly thing. What are you looking for anyway?" asked Gregory. The tapestry depicted a bunch of Trolls and a wizard wearing bright pink robes demonstrating en pointe to the trolls, who watched attentively, with minimal drool. Draco stood facing the other direction, but there was just a blank wall, the rare bit of empty space this high up. Normally the walls displayed paintings, tapestries, windows, dangerous ledges, or some knick-knack. But this hallway had ten solid empty feet, with nothing. Draco ran his fingers across the wall, feeling along the seams.

"I could have sworn there was a restroom here last week," said Draco. "Right between those suits of armor. I mean, I used it – really nice, better than the Prefect's restroom that has the heated pool - and I definitely recognize the tapestry," he waved back behind him. "I'm sure it was here."

"I don't imagine you could forget that," said Gregory, examining the background. "This will haunt my dreams, ah! Duck!"

Draco crouched down as several spells flew over his head. He glanced to the left and saw the Carrow sisters, Flora and Sheila poking around the corner firing spells. Hestia stood in a doorway on the right with another older Slytherin girl, Viola Richmond. What was it with the Slytherin girls? And didn't anybody aim for the chest anymore? Center of mass, hard to dodge. Maybe they just had terrible aim. Gregory dove across the hallway, firing blindly, and pulled himself behind the suit of armor for cover. Draco reached into his cloak and touched the vial of liquid luck, then put it back. This didn't seem that desperate.

"Retreat back around the corner on three," Gregory said and pointed his wand down the hallway and counted "one, two, Jellyfy." Draco ran the few steps to the corner and turned left into the pack of Slytherin boys.

"Oh, cra..."

Gregory heard Draco's shout, and then the Petrificus Totalus and then nothing.

Gregory fired off a few more spells at the now retreating girls and looked back at Draco's body, visible from the waist up as he'd fallen backwards.

"Goyle? This isn't personal. We all like you, Gregory," Marcus Flint's voice carried around the hall, "And we just need to teach your friend some manners. But you can walk away."

"You don't really expect that, do you Marcus?" Gregory shouted, then glanced at down the hallway. The ladies were slipping away. He didn't bother firing on them, but moved to get cover towards the corner.

"No, not really. But we are teammates and I," the words ended with a sickening crunch and some shouts, a stupefy, a curse he didn't recognize and Hermione Granger shouting Glisseo. There were several more shouts in response followed by the sound of tumbling. Gregory ran – no point in dodging when the enemy had no line-of-sight – and crouched over Draco's body then peeked around the corner. Marcus Flint stood doubled over, bleeding from his mouth, lower lip even larger than normal and one of his front teeth twisted slightly.

Gregory pulled Draco out of the line of fire and saw Lucian Bole, who Gregory had just taken the Beater position from, down on his hands and knees but still firing curses at Hermione. Terence Higgs, former seeker, cast an Expelliarumus and hit Granger squarely with it, her wand flying down the hall. Hermione just got up and started running towards Higgs. Gregory hit Bole with a Somnium just as Hermione slid into Higg's legs, knocking him over like a set of tenpens. They rolled over each other along the ground and then she was on him, throwing punches into his stomach.

Boles let out a few grunts and Hermione wrestled his wand away from him, barely pausing before leaping up and breaking into a graceful run. By this point Marcus had recovered and, spitting out his tooth, cast Protego. Gregory's stupefy was well aimed, but hit shields. Hermione cast a few Laganns and Gregory followed suit, but Marcus's shields held and he fired a powerful Ventus towards Gregory that sent several paintings flying off the wall, complaining loudly about students today as they clattered to the floor. Gregory ducked back just in time to see Hermione swinging through the air, legs around Marcus's neck, then her momentum flipped him off his feet just as she released her ankles and then landed next to him and simply kicked his wand away before hitting him with a stupefy.

"You've got to be kidding me," Gregory said under his breath. He walked over to Draco whose eyes followed his movements. Gregory cast finite incatatem. Draco popped up quickly, taking in the scene, while Gregory recovered the scattered wands.

"There were a few more on the stairs," Hermione said, "but I didn't see them before they slid away. Sorry. I guess it would have been useful to know who they were. But better safe than sorry." Gregory tossed Hermione's wand to her. "Thanks, Gregory."

Draco walked up to Hermione. "Are you all right? Thanks," he said, somewhat bashfully, "for everything." Draco inspected Higgs and Flint, both now moaning slightly, then stood up and looked at Hermione again. "If you want, I can fix up that bruise so it doesn't show until you can get it taken care of."

"No, I'm fine, Draco. It's lucky I was here."

"Yes," said Draco, "very lucky."

"No," said Gregory in an excited whisper, "there's no way she could do that. I couldn't do that move, it requires a good decade of martial arts training. That's Asian quality Shaolin type stuff. No way Hermione Granger just learns that." They were walking back after both offence classes, Draco lecture and the second year class. They'd stopped by the tapestry again and Draco asked Gregory to walk him through what happened - another after-action report, like the one he'd lectured on to the first year students.

"And yet she did it," Draco said quietly. "Or you imagined it."

"I did not imagine that," Gregory started and Draco just shook his head.

"No, I believe you, she really did it. You saw it, it's true. And you are confused." Draco let the words hang in the air as they walked down another flight of stairs. "How did her hair look? How did she look, while fighting."

Gregory considered. "I didn't get a good view, but I'd say normal. Why?"

"You said she tumbled on the ground, tackled Higgs and rolled and punched him. But she had no dirt or dust on her. Just one bruise. Her hair looked perfect, not even mussed, when I looked at her. I thought - I don't know - I thought I was infatuated with her."

"I'm infatuated with her right now, too," Gregory interrupted.

"Yes, I get that. I think I still am. But I think it's not just infatuation. I think she's got a glamour to keep her hair nice, repel dirt, the works. I mean, I can do all that but it's not permanent. If I'd gone flying through the air my hair would mess up. And she also has a glow. Maybe she's got some other spell that makes her graceful. She wasn't sweating, either, although the fight ended so fast that doesn't really mean anything."

Gregory nodded. "Yeah. Yes, that sounds right. And she was graceful, like you said. How did you know?"

"It's why I believe you. When I got hit, did you notice anything unusual?"

"I wasn't looking that way. I was covering you, remember? But you were awake when you the fight was over. But that spell doesn't put you to sleep..."

"It does if you hit the ground hard enough," said Draco, "but I didn't hit at all. Something caught me right before I hit the ground, then lowered me. It had to be her, unless we're saying there was someone else around. And, I'm not sure but I think she caught me with her foot." Draco remembered last night's lesson. "Do we have a bold prediction on what's going on?"

They walked along in silence for three flights of stairs.

"OK, let's just assume that she's become pretty amazing," said Gregory, "which we already knew, after Azkaban."

"Assuming Azkaban is true," said Draco, "which now seems likely." Gregory nodded. "She was always anti-bully, so maybe she's just lurking around to wreck vengeance on them."

"And not," said Gregory slowly, "following us around because Potter asked her to."

"Invisibly," Draco added.

"With martial arts skills I don't have after six years of training," Gregory said.

"That she never showed last year," finished Draco.

They walked back to the dorms in silence.

Horace Slughorn stared over his assembled Slytherin students, those who had been marched from the Headmistresses office after being caught for attempted bullying. They weren't impressive – even ignoring that they'd lost to a second year girl, albeit The Girl Who Revived – but he couldn't tolerate the pettiness, the lack of ambition.

These weren't ringleaders, the clever rarely got nabbed in the first sweep. These, he reflected, were minions. But as he looked along the worried faces, Professor Slughorn suspected the instigators would hear everything he'd say soon enough. He'd had the Headmistress send the bruised and defeated students to his potions classroom instead of meeting them in the dungeons, because the long walk allowed time to worry. He'd finished brewing a particularly nasty draught of Baneberry potion, room smelling pungent as if a fire burned rotting flesh that left students coughing and eyes watering. It took decades to acclimate to all the smells in a potions laboratory, and only the best Potions Masters could stomach them all.

Which didn't make it any more pleasant for him, but he showed no sign of distress, unlike his charges.

"Flint, m' boy. I'm inclined to overlook this whole thing," said Professor Slughorn, as Marcus Flint's face relaxed into a look of dumb relief, "since I would hate to lose the Quidditch cup as my first year. Oh, that wouldn't do. Wouldn't do at all, no matter how they change the rules. And if I suspend you, well, I'll have to investigate the rest of the team and and where would we be, hmm? Nowhere good." He turned his gaze to the other boys and noted, with satisfaction, their watering eyes. No doubt caused by the thick musk in the air, but if he needed to send them out in public others would assume they'd been crying.

"Still, I can't very well let you off without something. Must keep up appearances. Now," said Slughorn, shifting his considerable bulk, as the chair creaked plaintively, looking down at Flint, Higgs, and Bole, "I find it hard to believe that you have a serious grievance against Malfoy. None of you lost your parents. You might have a slight against Mr. Goyle, Bole, and Malfoy is a convenient excuse. I have my own theory, would you like to hear it?"

Judging from the nods, Professor Slughorn thought that they would.

"Given what I've heard about the attack, it seems that the Carrow sisters, who do have a reason to feel slighted, are offering …. certain incentives, or bounties." As he spoke, Slughorn carefully studied their faces and could tell that he was wrong. The dawning realization on Marcus Flint's face - the slow reveal that he probably could have asked for some favors - spoke volumes. But that same realization also meant that Slughorn had effectively punished those girls far worse than he could in any official capacity. He chuckled, more to himself than to keep up the charade.

"I thought as much. I was a young man, myself, and it's a rite of passage to allow yourself to be manipulated by some witch. You know the old saying, 'You can't fall into her arms without falling into her hands.' Ha! But, at some point you must be your own man. Why, get a reputation for doling out favors for any witch who just smiles at you ... well, you aren't a true Slytherin."

Terrence spoke up "Sir, it's not just..." Slughorn silenced him with a stare and a harrumph. He'd get the exact reason later, in his own time.

"I'm sure it's not just that, you may very well have legitimate complaints. But I expect them to be solved quietly. And I don't expect to listen to them myself, not today. If, in a week, a quiet week, you have complaints I'll take them up. But for now I want peace and quiet in my house. So I think we'll settle for just having you clean up this room as part of a detention, instead of discussing expulsions. Oh yes, I'm perfectly willing to clean house. And I find a more concrete mild threat now will often work when a distant but much greater threat doesn't."

"Greater threat, sir?" asked Boles.

"Why, with Lord Voldemort dead I can only think of three future dark lords, and you've managed to annoy them all during the last few weeks," said the Professor, easing out of his chair. "Scrub the glasswork well, and be sure not to spill any potions on you. It will burn through your skin. Give you some raging acne if you sniff too much of it, now that I think of it. You all know where everything goes, and I daresay it won't take you much more than four hours. I'll come check back after dinner." He strolled out the door.

"Three?" said Martin, as they glanced among themselves.

"Three?" said Gregory, sounding surprised.

"That's what Slughorn told them," said Daphne Greengrass, who'd heard about the entire incident the day before. The entire dating relationship of the upper classes had gone through a period of turbulence over the last twenty four hours, including numerous slaps, hexes, curses, pleading and breakups, although a few new relationships formed as well. The witches gossip network nearly collapsed from the strain of keeping up. "Said there were three future Dark Lords. I mean, I can see Potter and Draco, no offense."

"None taken," said Draco, with a small bow, where he sat on his bed, perusing the latest letter from Mother, "although I think he was just trying to convince them to back down."

Daphne, sitting in Draco's chair at the desk, nodded. "Well, obviously, but that still begs the question as to who the third Dark Lord would be."

Gregory paced slowly. "Granger? I mean, I can't see it, although it would be somewhat great," Draco looked up at him quizzically, "I mean, come on. A Dark Gryffindor? With a Phoenix? And she likes us. We could do a lot worse, you know," Draco went back to reading his letter with a sigh and Daphne just shook her head. "I did say somewhat great," Gregory said, morosely.

"If it were me," said Draco, "it would just be a mind game. Slughorn didn't mean anyone in particular, he just knew that everyone expects there to be one or two, so by saying three he makes them all stop and think. Which is probably a novel experience for them, but sadly not habit forming. In any case, I can't think of another credible Dark Wizard of our generation..." Draco's voice trailed off for a second, then picked back up. "I mean, certainly we could have one, but nobody seems like a threat yet. No, he was just messing with them."

"You sound like you've just convinced yourself," said Daphne. "But you haven't convinced me. In any case, I figured you'd want to know. Do you have any idea why they targeted you?"

"Thank you," said Draco. "As to why, simply because they can. They've gotten a few shots in, but not enough to claim victory. Now it's more about honour than any reason."

Chapter 17: The Halo Effect

"Do not get greedy. Have partners share your gains. This provides allies against losses." - Lucius Malfoy

The Bayesian Conspiracy met after dinner at least once a week, tonight's session had just passed the two hour mark.

"All of these ideas," said Neville, "they let us check a solution. But they don't help us come up with the answer." Harry just raised his eyebrows and looked around the table, like he did when he wanted people to come up with the solution themselves.

"Coming up with a solution is harder," said Draco, "But checking it is easy. Does it work is yes or no. How does it work, that could be anything."

"Proving a solution is like a fixed Transfiguration," Hermione offered, "you go from stone to wood and back. But even that requires lots of different spells, hundreds for every form combination. Free transfiguration can do anything, but we all know how hard that is." Hermione felt smug having worked out the metaphor. She missed being in class and getting the right answer, even though she knew it was somewhat small of her.

Harry finally spoke up, "And coming up with a solution is really hard. Even I don't get it right often. But what I do is that I check my solution instead of just trying it, and that lets me discard my failures faster, and then I try again. If nobody sees you fail a few times," he chuckled," you'll get a reputation as being able to do anything by just snapping your fingers. I'm not always right, merely less wrong. And to most people that seems like magic."

Harry's mirror made a buzzing noise, and he took it out and started a quiet conversation, then said "I think now's a good time to stop." Daphne checked the time and, letting out a small eep, grabbed her scrolls and ran off. Draco jotted a few notes down on a scroll, planning to summarize and expand later in his journal.

"Draco," said Hermione, "Do you have a few minutes?"

He looked up, perplexed. "Sure. One second." He wrote a few more words, more reminders than detailed notes.

Harry said, "I'll see you later, everyone. I do have some things to do." He put away his mirror. Draco caught Hermione's look, but Harry just shook his head. "It's not that important." He walked out of the classroom, Neville beside him, and their voices drifted down the hall as Draco put down his quill and looked across the desk at Hermione.

Draco could see the telltale signs of the glamour, now. That should make her perfection less impressive, but it didn't. Knowing something on an intellectual level doesn't necessarily turn off emotions.

"How are things going, Draco?" she asked. Hermione stared at him intently, trying to read his reactions. She felt like she'd been getting better at reading people. Her magic helped her perceptions, if she focused on it. She really hoped that came from the Unicorn side of the enhancement, and not the troll side. She preferred not to think of herself as one-third Troll.

"Fine, Hermione. People miss you in class, of course."

"I find that hard to believe," she said, shaking her head, and noticing how Draco watched her hair.

"Oh, they thought they didn't want you in classes for the first few days." Draco's pitched his voice up like Pansy Parkinson. "Where's little miss know-it-all? Where can she be?" He dropped his voice back to normal, "but it turns out that when little miss know-it-all isn't there with the answer then the Professor could call on anyone, and that's worse."

"If you are Pansy Parkinson, sure," laughed Hermione, "I suspect you know the answers."

Draco smiled, "I said people missed you, Hermione, not that I did." Draco's smile looked relaxed, not forced, not beaming, but enough of a smile to show he was joking. She let out a little laugh, and Draco's smile relaxed a bit more. "So, what did you want to talk about?"

"I'm worried about you," she said and Draco interrupted her with a wave.

"It's not that I don't appreciate what you did, Hermione, and I'm not going to lie and say I have it all under control, but it isn't helping my situation as much as you might hope and I think," Draco finally had to pause for a breath, just barely.

"I'm worried about you and Harry," Hermione said, exasperated.

"Oh." Draco paused and fiddled with his quill, thinking. "Why?" Between the pause and the interruption, Hermione felt pleased that Draco treated her more like a friend and less like a tool he manipulated. Or maybe Harry's abrasive manner had been rubbing off.

"Well, you live with him, but you don't trust him. He told me – please don't be mad – about the chess game, and the Slytherin duel before that."

Draco blushed.

"He didn't mention all of the parts of the duel, he is your friend after all. But I heard lots of gossip. Anyway, I understand why intellectually its hard to trust Harry, but can you please? I mean, I trust him. Doesn't that count for something?" Hermione considered batting her eyes, but she already felt guilty, using Draco's infatuation to help her gauge how much she should trust him.

"It does," Draco stammered, "of course it does. But … what we've been learning here is how keep our judgment when we're biased. If Harry were here, he'd say something like 'Hermione Granger is difficult to fool, which reduces the odds of Harry being a future Dark Lord significantly.'"

"But not to zero." Draco just nodded. "I understand that, Draco. That makes sense. In fact, Harry told me a story. After Professor Quirrell taught him to lose he asked if there was anything he could say to convince the Professor he wouldn't turn evil, and the Professor just replied 'You could raise your right hand,' meaning that there was nothing that someone as clever as Harry could say that would comfort him. So we have to judge Harry by his actions, not his words. And that's going to take time."

"I knew that," Draco said. "But it isn't just time. I can't judge Harry's actions if I can't see them."

"The time will come, things have to line up a bit first. Please, Draco, don't make it even more difficult for him."

Draco slumped in his chair. "Even more difficult?"

"You, you don't see it?" Her eyes semi-closed, "I get it now. He hides it from you, doesn't want to look weak. He runs off every time." Hermione thought, deciding if she wanted to reveal what she'd assumed Draco had already noticed. She said, "Boys!" with a snort. "Why don't they just talk instead of posture?"

Hermione saw Draco's bewildered look, and sighed.

"What did Harry tell you, about Voldemort? I have to ask because I promised him I wouldn't tell anyone details."

Draco got up and started pacing. "He didn't tell me anything," Draco said, sounding slightly hurt. "But I have my guesses. I'm not sure how Professor Quirrell is involved, or any details really. But, well, they came up with a plan to bring you back and attack Voldemort. The Professor took the brunt of the attack, maybe sacrificed himself since he was dying. At the time, I didn't think you were involved at all, and that was just Harry being Harry, bringing you back somehow. But after the summer and what Gregory saw when you fought Flint …. I don't know. You've been hiding your powers haven't you?"

Hermione nodded slightly. "I want to be treated like a normal girl, not like Harry was treated. For as long as I can."

"So, I'm not sure anymore exactly who defeated Voldemort, but Harry was there, if not the driving force. Despite the fact that he appeared to not be there."

"How do you think he did that," she asked.

Draco shot Hermione a look, and then said. "I have some theories. But he hasn't told me how. I don't think he'll ever tell me, and I'm OK with it. I'd like to know the details, of course..."

"And that's it? Harry didn't tell you anything else? Professor Quirrell died. You never thought to ask yourself if Harry got away without a scratch?" Hermione had an edge in her voice, and saw Draco's shock. She realized that no, he hadn't actually asked himself. Which wasn't too surprising. Harry never seemed to get scratched. Before she died Hermione had seen Harry scared, but never actually hurt in some surprisingly dangerous situations. And everyone had been so young. Harry explained that most people never thought about death (and by extension, injury) until they'd seen it first hand. There was no reason Draco would be different.

"Wait, you have a Phoenix. Harry built Peverell Hospital. Whatever happened to him is fixed." Draco's voice had a note of accusation.

"Have you ever heard of hypergraphia, Draco? People with it suffer a compulsion to write things out. They can't stop writing, not until they are exhausted. Harry doesn't have that, exactly, but he got cursed in the battle. You know he was already a bit obsessed and his methods made him …. odd. But now it's more of a compulsion. He literally can't do things unless he reasons out all of the consequences." Harry wouldn't be happy about this, Hermione thought, but it was a close enough explanation to be true.

"What kind of curse does that?" Draco asked.

"The kind that Voldemort casts, specifically designed to slow down Harry Potter. No, I don't know why Voldemort didn't just kill him. Maybe he worried about the spell rebounding, like it did when Harry was a baby. Voldemort cast a curse that would hurt Harry more than anyone. And now Harry has to spend hours and hours making decisions that he could have made in a second last year. He's …. too rational, maybe."

Hermione paused. "I guess you don't see it because he's exhausted when he goes back to his dorm. And he's not making decisions then, not really. He's just teaching and hanging out with the few friends he has left. I think Harry would say that the odds that Draco Malfoy is actually a good person and Harry's friend have shot up dramatically, so I just want you to give him time and not do anything rash."

Draco gathered his notes and they both got up to head out. "I wasn't planning on doing anything rash," Draco said defensively. Draco opened the door, quickly glancing at the empty hallway.

"Nobody ever does," Hermione said as she walked through the door.

"I suppose not," said Draco, shutting the door behind him.

Chapter 21: October

"When paying for information, you will frequently overpay.

This is unavoidable, and do not fret about it (unless tricked).

Consider it a balance for the times a crucial fragment falls into your lap because the seller is unaware of its value.

After all, If you knew how much to pay, you wouldn't be buying."

- Lucius Malfoy

"Anyway, the trick to it is to flick your wand right as you..." Blaise Zabini froze when Harry Potter walked into the second year boys' room. Theodore Nott looked over his shoulder, following Blaise's eyes.

Harry asked "Theodore. Am I interrupting? I'd like to talk to General Zabini."

"We can finish later," Theodore said. "It's no problem."

"Thanks," said Harry. "Do you mind if we walk? I have to go somewhere and this way we won't be disturbed..." Blaise stood up, smoothing out his robes, and walked beside Harry. They quickly went through the common room, past the prefect's room, and into the dungeons. All through the trip Potter asked his opinion about last weekend's battle. The fourth year armies had fought on the roof of Hogwarts, but hadn't been allowed any brooms. Blaise recognized it as small talk, which did seem like Potter's typical style.

"Anyway, General," said Harry, "What I really wanted to talk about is a small conspiracy I'd like you to join. We're disguised as a study group. I suppose we're actually studying something." They crossed the creaking bridge over the main stream, air brackish but not unpleasant. Harry quieted as they passed three first years returning from classes.

"What do you study?" Blaise asked. His brown eyes warily darting around. Potter was Draco's friend and had a reputation narrowly outrunning the chaos which followed him constantly around, but this didn't feel like a trap. Still, you couldn't be too careful.

"Decision making. Science. Problem solving. How to think and how to avoid mistakes. 'Rationality' is the technical term." They passed the Bloody Baron, who was talking to several of the paintings lining the Hall.

Blaise considered for twenty-five steps. "That sounds useful. What's the catch?"

"There are two. First, You have to learn to admit mistakes. That sounds easy, but it's surprisingly hard. One conspirator likened it to a 'Dark Ritual,' you sacrifice the ability to lie to yourself. Lots of people can't do that, and they suffer mental anguish," Harry paused then took a lighter tone, "I prefer to think of it as growing pains."

They had exited Slytherin proper and stepped into the common dungeons. They'd diverted from the stone stairs that led up into Hogwarts, and went down a Hallway that glowed slightly with no apparent lights. Blaise recognized the area, Potions was here, but they passed that and went further down the hall, footsteps making small squeeking sounds as their damp footprints connected with the stone. Harry Potter stopped in front of a door.

"As for the second catch." Harry opened the door and walked into the classroom, Blaise following.

"Malfoy," Blaise said flatly, as Draco looked up from the desk, closing a small black book he'd apparently been writing in.

"Don't dismiss it out of hand," said Harry, "Draco suggested inviting you."

"So I can be your lackey?"

"I didn't have to invite you," said Draco harshly, "and lackeys are easy. I put your name up because you are going to be absolutely slaughtered in the battles if you fall too far behind. It's too useful. You have some weaknesses, and you can usually work around them, but Neville's joined and Potter's teaching his special creativity. That's a serious challenge, if Neville learns first. You have potential and this would help," Draco's voice held a hint of anger, "but if you are willing to throw an advantage away just because I'm involved..."

"You are in Chaos now. Why help Basilisk?" Blaise sounded incredulous, but he sat down.

"I wouldn't expect you to believe me, but Basilisk is the de facto Slytherin army and a poor showing looks bad. Not on me personally, but on everyone else. I'm not going to go easy on you if we meet on the field. But all of our armies aren't doing well. It would be nice to have one that everyone could rally behind."

"And of course you are trying to save our House," said Blaise.

Harry watched. He'd expressed worry, but Draco had been right that inviting Blaise could help Slytherin, even if he probably wasn't ready. Draco needed the ally, this would be Draco's olive branch. Harry wanted to jump in and argue this, but Draco had asked for his silence unless things looked hopeless. This might have normally presented a problem - keeping quiet wasn't Harry's strong suit - but some things Draco said tickled a memory, one that Harry couldn't quite place ...

"Yes. I have my plots," Draco was saying, "I've been fairly open about them. Look, I know you think it's not clever to reveal too much to others, and you think I'm making the same mistake. Maybe I am. I look confident on the outside, but sometimes I worry. Did Harry tell you about the cost of admitting you are wrong? It's a real cost, and ... well, maybe it cost me some confidence."

Harry's expression showed confusion, as he tried to remember why this seemed so familiar. It wasn't what Draco was saying, more like how he said it.

Draco saw Harry, but focused on Blaise who still had arms crossed in front of his body. Not a good sign, but he hadn't left yet.

"You don't know much about me," said Blaise. "You don't know what it's like, how I grew up."

"No," said Draco softly, "I just lost my Father recently. But I never excluded you. Not deliberately. Look, at the beginning of last year we were all scrabbling and jockeying. I had a head start. It's not fair, but you can't expect me to give up advantages."

"And you can't expect me to not resent that," said Blaise. "You ignored me, didn't even treat me like a rival."

"Look, I admit I've been distracted. In my defense, I was trying to keep up with the Boy-Who-Lived and the Girl-Who-Revived," Draco held up his hands, "although no, we didn't know that at the time. I was almost murdered! Nobody could compete with that. And, I swear I'll deny this if you ever say it, you are tough to read, Zabini. One day you act shy, lost in your own thoughts, and keep to yourself. The next day you're the life of the party. Most people I can get easily," Draco snapped his fingers, then shrugged. "But you...so yes, I do want your help in saving Slytherin and even just figuring out who is attacking me, but that's not a prerequisite. You are in for this if you want it. I'll even try to teach you the Patronus spell, no strings attached. Although some people just can't learn it."

Blaise considered this, "Who else is in this group?"

"If you join you'll know. But if you do join and rat us out to the others, then you've made an enemy, and not just us." Draco sounded firm.

Blaise unfolded his arms. "No strings attached?"

Robert Jugson sat down next to Draco at the breakfast table. There was plenty of space, just Goyle, Greengrass, and Potter at this end of the table.

"Pass the croissants, please." Draco simply passed them across, then slid a small jar of strawberry jam along with it. Potter and Goyle were discussing the Slytherin Quiddich team's chances. Well, Goyle was talking about it and Potter merely asking a few questions. Robert Jugson ignored the looks from the other end of the table, where the upperclass students normally sat. Draco finished another piece of cantaloupe and took a sip of milk, washing away the fruit's sweetness, not rushing.

"I've been wondering, Mr. Jugson," Draco said, putting down his glass, "when do older students make career decisions? Goyle has his bright future as a professional Quidditch player, but what about the rest of us? How does it work, exactly? I mean, you graduate in the Spring."

Robert finished chewing on his croissant, then swallowed noisily. "I've been thinking about taking a job at Borgin and Burkes, I'd talked with pop about that ... earlier. It isn't difficult, they are family friends. But now it seems pointless. I'm going to spend a century showing wares to customers? It would be one thing if I owned the store. I've been talking to Professor Slughorn, my Potions grades are OK so he might be able to get me an apprenticeship at an Apothecary."

"Do you enjoy Potions," asked Gregory.

"Not really. But at least I'd be making something. Beats selling. In any case, Draco, I don't see that you have to worry. Your family has money."

"Not as much as we did, and a lot of it will be gone by the time I graduate. Best for me to start thinking of it now."

Draco was thinking about other opportunities.

Draco sat up with a start. He'd been asleep, face down. The room wasn't too dark, the full moon had already risen and he could read the letter he'd started, sitting by the desk next to his closed diary.

Mum,

Of course your happiness is important to me - I do not think it is too soon - but I've already explained how precarious my position is and surely there are others ...

Draco crumpled the letter, he could never send that. He leaned down and picked his wand off the floor. What time was it? He groaned to himself, Don't overexert, you need some rest and crawled into bed.

"Harry, is luck real? What's the scientific perspective?" Gregory said, not looking up from his game of (muggle) chess with Draco. Harry had ordered a Muggle set. Draco's pieces protested mightily at the thought of not using their full skills and had mutinied at the thought of obediently following orders. Draco and Gregory's first game where they physically moved the pieces resulted in a dozen small cuts and bites and after the Silver Queen collapsed in a few-blown tantrum they'd just given up and asked Harry for a set.

"Well. It's complicated," said Harry. "Variance is real. You have streaks of good events and bad events, however you define good and bad. Most people notice some of those streaks and forget the rest or the non-streaky balancing luck. So, from a strictly math point of view, luck just is." Harry paused. "Actually, being lucky is a psychological trait."

"How can that be?" asked Draco, game forgotten for a moment.

"They did studies on people who considered themselves lucky and those who thought they were cursed with bad luck. When it came to random chance - rolling dice or whatever - there was no difference. Random is random. Then they did other tests, and in one of them the researchers handed each subject a newspaper and asked them to count the pictures. The lucky people got it much faster."

"How could they possibly do that?" said Gregory. Draco realized another nice benefit of muggle chess is that the pieces didn't grumble when you ignored them or took too long to move.

"One of the headlines said 'There are 37 pictures.' The answer was literally printed right there on the second page. The people who felt lucky were really just more attentive to non-traditional opportunities. Both groups had the same random things happen, but the 'lucky' noticed good things that happened to them. At least, that's the theory. The researchers built in a short cut, but the lucky people tended to notice it more The 'unlucky' people plodded along and counted the pictures, so focused on what they were supposed to do that they never noticed the opportunity."

"Which means you can train yourself to be lucky, in a way," said Gregory.

Harry nodded. "That's what we've been doing. Learning how to think means learning to take advantage of unexpected situations."

Draco, grumbling, handed Gregory a Knut. Gregory chuckled and made his next move.

Michael MacNair stood in the depths of the dungeon, looking around at the robed figures. He put his hands on his hips, exasperated. "Look, I didn't care one way or the other before. Draco's a twerp, but our twerp. In case you didn't notice, Salazer practically invented arrogant and snooty. If anything, we need Malfoy as a bulwark against Potter, at least until Zabini comes around. I almost turned you into Professor Slughorn, and collected the bounty."

"But then everyone would think you were Malfoy's puppet, or scared," said Flora Carrow, sneering. "But we don't care why you're here, as long as you are now. Isn't that right?" The other six robes nodded. "We should attack him soon," came Hestia's voice, beside Flora.

"No," said Michael, "not now. We'd be expelled." The others gasped, apparently willing to risk grievous injury over expulsion, but he just continued. "I'm not just making this up, Slughorn told me himself at dinner the other night that he'd expel anyone foolish enough to get caught messing with Malfoy. He was very emphatic about that, foolish enough to get caught."

Another robe chimed in, voice husky and muffled by a spell, "We shouldn't hesitate. You can see him, making more and more allies every day. And not just the younger students..."

Michael cut off husky voice. "If we wait just a few weeks, I think we'll have an opportunity, and his allies won't matter."

The robes crowded in to listen.

Draco went flying through the air, then landed with an oomph onto the soft grass. He rolled onto his stomach, robes smudged green and brown, and pulled himself onto his knees, slamming his fist angrily into the grass and taking in deep steady breaths.

"You expect too much," Vince said calmly, with no hint of reproach. "We've been training for years. You've only been practicing a few weeks. Give it time. Your stamina is getting better, too." They watched Gregory instruct Neville and Harry. "They aren't doing any better than you," he said in low tones, "and imagine how Gregory and I feel, seeing what you can do with a wand. A head start is a big deal. Mastery takes time."

Gregory was now sparring with the other two, and even Draco could see they didn't stand a chance, wouldn't stand a chance. But they had gotten better. Neville looked surprisingly comfortable, sparring, and Draco heard him singing "doom doom doom" quietly, before looking up.

"Harry," Neville said, dropping his guard, "The doom song is the bad guy's music!" Gregory chuckled.

"But it's catchy," retorted Harry, launching an attack that Gregory parried easily.

Harry came up from out of his trunk while they were doing homework. Draco and Gregory had agreed that Harry's habit of disappearing down there for hours on end was disconcerting, even though it made sense. He was carrying two books. Draco glanced at the spine of the top book and read off the title. Influence: The Psychology of Persuasion.

"Draco, you did well with Blaise the other night," Harry said.

Gregory glanced over at Harry, then went back to the letter he was writing his mother.

"You sound surprised?" Draco's voice said, dripping with sarcastic hurt. "Seriously Harry, the trick with Blaise is to get angry with him, just a little. That let's him know that he's worth my time, that he's important. And he is, just not as much as he hopes. Still, if he'd get over his inferiority complex from last year and those issues with his mother he could do well." Draco had gotten up and started pacing, as he normally did whenever he wasn't writing. Draco worried he spent too much time sitting down, and needed to stretch.

"You say the trick like you used only one," said Harry, and now Gregory put down his quill and slid his chair around, interested.

"A conversation is like a sword fight," said Gregory, "even I know that. How long were you talking? Of course you'd have lots to discuss."

"No," said Harry, dropping one book on his bed and flipping through the hardcover, "I meant technique. It's like you were cold-reading Blaise, I know it's in here somewhere." He kept flipping through pages.

"Cold reading?" Gregory asked.

"Trying to get someone to believe you know a lot about them when you've never met them. Tricking them into telling you stuff and making them think you've said it first."

"But Draco already knows Blaise," Gregory protested. "Why would he need to do that?"

Draco nodded. "Of course I know all about Blaise. As for techniques? Well, let's see. I empathized with him, I showed some weakness but not too much. Admitting that I wore a mask and wasn't as confident as I looked. That let him view us as similar, so more empathy although strictly speaking that's a separate technique. Finding connections between us, points of similarity. Although Blaise brought up the fact that we're both Fatherless first. Let's see ... I appealed to his vanity. I didn't try to hide the fact that I stood to gain something from this. I threatened him if he revealed us which treated him as an equal. What else ... I maybe garnered sympathy with almost being murdered, though I doubt that worked. And standard compliments."

Harry stopped flipping his book pages. "Standard compliments? Standard? I found it. Have you ever heard of the Forer Effect? Or P.T. Barnum?" Draco and Gregory both shook their heads. "I suppose not. Is there a Wizard book you learned this from?"

Draco shrugged, he'd stopped pacing and stretched out his arms above him, pulling them back behind his head, and his spine made a slight crack. "Ah! Better. No, just tutors and Father. Why?"

"Forer demonstrated that people would believe you possessed deep insight into their personalities if you just gave vague, slightly contradictory compliments. You know, stuff like 'Sometimes you feel shy and sometimes you feel outgoing.' You don't say how often, but everyone feels shy sometimes and outgoing other times. Even the biggest introverts and extroverts, even if they don't act on it. You said exactly that to Blaise and that's a standard compliment?"

Harry thrust the book underneath Draco's nose, pointed to Forer's list. Draco read it.

"I wouldn't use the one about sexuality for another few years. I assume Forer was older when he made this? And I wouldn't dare call Zabini's expectations unrealistic, given the circumstances, although they are. He's no Dark Wizard, whatever he thinks. He's not even a Minister of Magic - although I suppose if he works hard and stays useful - and I doubt Blaise is aiming lower than that. Good list, though."

He passed the book over to Gregory, while Harry spoke up, voice rising dramatically.

"Practically everything you said to him was on this list! You used five of these compliments directly. You implied at least two … no three more! Now that I think about it, you used one on yourself, which would create empathy. I'd read this before and I still couldn't remember exactly what struck me as odd until I read it again. How do you know all that?"

"People skills," Draco said in a mocking tone. He'd always wanted to throw that line back into Harry's face, and now seemed like a good time.

"Good list," Gregory agreed, handing Harry the book back and returning to his homework.

"Did you ever notice," said Ginny as she walked out of the first year lecture, passing General Malfoy in the rush to leave class, "that the train ride and first day of school seemed to last forever, but then time just started flying?"

"Of course it does," said Luna airily, "It always does that. The calendar shows all days as equal squares, but that's just a conspiracy perpetrated by gnomes and airlines. Some days are much much longer than others, of course. Why, some days can be longer than entire months."

In her office, Minerva McGonnagal dropped what she was doing and ran over to inspect her strange semi-cylinder, which had suddenly made that noise again.

Draco walked around Peverell, this time in the recovery lounge. He watched as several wizards who'd just taken the cure woke up and went to one of the full length mirrors to examine their recovered youth. They gasped, jumped up and down, shouted and laughed as they examined themselves. Several Aurors, including Li, watched as orderlies brought in still unconscious patients into the newly emptied beds. People didn't need long to recover from the treatment.

Alastor Moody appeared through the doorway from the visitor area, passing one of the exiting patients and growling as he spotted Draco.

Draco did a double-take, recognizing the stance Harry used that morning in the dungeons after Draco's abduction. Moody held his wand up high, near eye level. Just like Harry had. Mad-Eye spun around on his heel, taking in the full room, then barked 'Boy!' as he finished the circle. Draco jumped despite himself, then calmed down.

"Don't like these tests," said the grizzled Auror, "and it's not like you lot are going to think of something I've forgotten."

Draco was inclined to agree, but simply said "Good morning, sir," as politely as possible.

"If you want to do something useful for me," said Moody, "you can just tell me about your cane." Draco started to answer, sneering, when he felt the colors of the world invert, like the room had turned to black with only white outlines. A second later, it snapped back to normal. "That's what I thought," said Moody stomping off even as Draco started yelling after him.

"How dare you!" Draco said, not moving. "Students aren't to be abused by wizards who imagine themselves as warriors of justice ..."

"This isn't Hogwarts, lad. And quiet, or I'll turn you into a ferret," he said, stomping off. Draco, still spluttering, turned to an appalled Auror Li, who just shrugged.

"Harry, he read my mind! We've got to do something about it! That's not right, you more than anyone must see that." Draco's voice, normally so calm, seemed strained, which made sense. A Malfoy must value secrets more highly than almost anyone, and to have them stolen...

Harry sat on his trunk, reading, a concerned look on his face. He'd already heard Alastor's report about the cane. Draco could disappear with it, could make the cane seemingly come to life and - most intriguingly - summon it. And Draco hadn't been lying earlier to Harry, Draco was still investigating the rest of the powers. Alastor had wanted to investigate more, to dig deeper into Draco's mind. He'd said there was "something strange about that's boy's mind," but he'd followed Harry's instructions and only looked for information about the cane. Well, that's what he told me, at least. Moody had asked to investigate further, but Harry had said no, sick at having to have checked in the first place.

Now he had to mollify Draco.

"What do you expect me to do about it," Harry asked plaintively. "I mean, he's technically correct. You were at the hospital, not on school grounds."

"I'm not a fool, Harry. I know you can do something. You consult on security, so he must listen to you, whether he likes it or not. And you aren't in second year classes, or even third or fourth. I've asked around. And if you aren't in classes you've got pull with the Headmistress. I don't mind this, I don't care about your secrets, I just want you to use your power! You and Hermione are both Heads of a Noble House. You could go in front of the Wizengamot and demand redress. I could do it, too, but it would take longer and"

"I need him," said Harry, face flushed. "I wish I didn't, he's got a bad reputation, but you don't hire veelas to run security. You hire cranky old ex-Aurors who'd just as soon as invade your privacy as kill you."

Draco looked at Harry, "Well, I'm not going back there then. Apparently I'll just use my extra time to study for my O.W.L.S. and go in front of the Wizengamot myself."

"I will not go around provoking strong and vicious enemies," Harry said in his best imitation of Professor Quirrell.

"How did I provoke him?" screeched Draco. "He's been after my family for years, well before Voldemort came along."

"And your family did nothing to draw his attention? Sorry, that's not fair to you," said Harry. "But I'll talk to him, get him to back down."

Author's Note - The opening quote is based on a quote from economist (and youngest winner of the Nobel Prize in economics) Kenneth Arrow. "The value of information is frequently not known in any meaningful sense to the buyer; if, indeed, he knew enough to measure the value of the information, he would know the information itself." This is similar to puzzles where knowing that a solution exists (or that another party has solved it), leads to the correct solution.

Chapter 22: Reflections, Pt 3

"Father, if Voldemort was so powerful, why did he need any Death Eaters?"

"He lacked the patience for administration. Also, he needed an audience to truly enjoy himself."

- Conversation between Draco and Lucius Malfoy, circa 1989

Draco paced back and forth, staring at the blank wall. It had been a risk, ditching Gregory, but the entire castle was out celebrating Harry Potter Day – except for Harry himself, who had disappeared into his chest after breakfast – so Draco felt safe from ambush. And in any case, he had his liquid luck and wand out, he'd simply stun anyone he saw.

Draco paced back and forth, staring at the featureless wall. Harry told them to make bold predictions. Draco had decided to make the boldest one he could – this room appeared in response to student's desires, and fulfill them … somehow. You had to really need it, not just find it convenient. There was no reason for this to be true, or at least for this prediction to be any more true than some other one. But, Draco remembered what the Weasley twins said about summoning the Sorting Hat, so it wasn't entirely unprecedented.

If Draco's prediction didn't pan out, he'd learn something. And if it worked … invaluable.

Draco started his experiment. He took a deep breath and closed his eyes.

I really need to know if Harry Potter will turn out to be a Dark Lord. It's the most important question I can ask, not just for me but for everyone, and there's no easy answer. I need to know. Draco took several deep breaths, concentrating.,When he opened his eyes Draco saw a small, solid door in the blank wall. Draco blinked again, then quickly opened the door. Before, where there had been a clean, polished bathroom complete with sinks and a sauna, stood a small wooden room.

Draco stepped inside, closing the door behind him, when he heard the voice.

"Hello, Tom," said Albus Dumbledore.

Draco froze. "Headmaster?" Draco ran forward and saw a giant piece of glass floating gently in the middle of the room, a portal to another room. Dumbeldore stood in the other room, just beyond the portal, which was surrounded by a gold frame. The frame anchored the room around it, as if it alone was real and the two rooms, the one Draco stood in and the one Dumbledore occupied, were merely illusion.

Draco stopped, frozen by Albus Dumbledore's piercing glare.

"They said you were lost. And how did you know about..."

Dumbledore's face, so hard a moment ago, became bewildered. "Quirinus? What -"

Draco looked confused, and he stuttered out another "Headmaster?"

"Well," said Albus Dumbledore. "I do feel stupid."

"Sir, I don't understand. You are supposed to give me advice. I thought this room would ..." but Dumbledore spoke right through him.

"There I am, searching so hard for Voldemort's shade, never noticing that the Defense Professor of Hogwarts is a sickly, half-dead victim possessed by a spirit far more powerful than himself. I would call it senility, if so many others had not missed it as well."

This isn't Dumbledore. This is a ... movie of Dumbledore, perhaps. A shade. Draco waved and shouted, but the Albus Dumbledore in the mirror - the mirror which did not reflect the room he was in, but of another room, more of a cave really – didn't answer. The only one in that other room was Dumbledore. After a moment, Draco registered the actual words he'd heard. Quirrell was Voldemort. Draco sat down, practically collapsed. I made the same mistake Father did. I didn't recognize my enemy. For a year.

Draco caught himself. If this is true.

"Oh, yes indeed," Albus Dumbledore said in level tones. "Your acting was perfect; I confess myself utterly deceived. Quirinus Quirrell seemed - what is the term I am looking for? Ah yes, that is the word. He seemed sane."

This is not necessarily true. Why do you believe this is true? This is an illusion. Draco wanted to believe this is a lie, but it felt correct. Why would this room, or whoever created it, lie to Draco. What would be the point? That seemed far fetched, and if Hogwarts itself was lying to him, Draco didn't know what to think.

Draco considered what he heard. Professor Quirrell was Voldemort? Did that make sense? He'd been powerful enough, but ... it didn't fit. Did it? Draco sat and listened, listened to only one side of the conversation as best he could. Would anyone fake half a converstion to fool me? Actually, this seems exactly like the sort of thing Father would expect Dumbledore to do.

"The Boy-Who-Lived came out of it well enough. Tried to turn him into you, did you? Instead you turned yourself into a corpse, and Harry Potter became the wizard you should have been."

Draco snapped back his full attention at the mention of Harry Potter. If Professor Quirrell was Voldemort, what did that imply? Draco's stomach knotted, that sentence could be interpreted many ways, but they didn't seem good...

"All of Tom Riddle's icy brilliance, tamed to the service of James and Lily's warmth and love. I wonder how you felt when you saw what Tom Riddle could have become, if he had grown up in a loving family?"

Draco relaxed, and realized he'd been holding his breath. This was the proof he'd searched for. Dumbledore knew about Harry. Dumbledore didn't know about Voldemort, exactly, but Dumbledore trusted Harry. Clearly there was some connection between Voldemort and Potter, but Harry had become – better. Draco started laughing.

"I suppose the humor of the situation would be lost on you."

He's not reacting to me. Is he? He wasn't before.

"How I laughed when I realized it! When I saw you had made a Good Voldemort to oppose the evil one - ah, how I laughed! I never had the steel for my role, but Harry Potter shall be more than equal to it, when he comes into his power. Though I suppose Harry shall have to find some other Dark Lord to vanquish for it, since you will not be there."

Draco watched the one sided exchange of the Dumbledore and Voldemort's argument, the Headmaster said he wouldn't give in despite Voldemort's hostages. This was odd, why did Dumbledore not attack Voldemort? Why was he not defending? Why were they talking, instead of fighting?

I went down this entire path because Harry Potter spoke with Voldemort, and here Dumbledore did it too. Draco paused, them remembered to add. If this is true. Does anyone just attack their enemy?

Dumbledore knew Voldemort's true name, he must have taught him. Professor Quirrell - Voldemort - must have known about Harry on the very first day of classes, known about their relationship. Now that Draco thought about it, Quirrell practically devoted his first two classes to Harry. Oh, he'd involved Draco and Hermione. But mainly Harry. Quirrell mentored Harry through the year, but had it been much more extensively than he'd taught Draco?

Harry probably didn't even know that Quirrell was Voldemort, everyone thought Voldemort died. Harry would consider it … irrational to worry about, until he had proof.

Draco now had a perfectly good explanation why Harry Potter had been on good terms with Voldemort until he killed him. At some point Harry deduced Voldemort's true nature and then they had fought, and Harry had won.

Draco's train of thought was interrupted by the name "Harry Potter," the Headmaster breathed. "What are you doing here?"

Draco glanced around, instinctively, to see if he'd been discovered. He turned back to see Dumbledore's frantic "No! No! No!" and watched as Dumbledore tossed away his wand and a rod that Draco recognized as the Line of Merlin Unbroken.

Then there was a flicker, and Dumbledore was gone.

The Headmaster reappeared with the words "Hello, Tom."

Draco watched again, paying attention, surprise replaced with concentration. He watched a third time.

Harry could be the hostage. Dumbledore had then conceded defeat rather than have Voldemort kill Harry. That made sense.

Or Harry had betrayed Dumbledore while working with Voldemort, who he betrayed later. That seemed … less likely. But not impossible.

Or Harry had stumbled onto the final duel between the two greatest living wizards and somehow accidentally messed up Dumbledore's plan. That hypothesis … could not be rejected out of hand. General Chaos had that effect on people.

Draco, after several repetitions, tenatively decided against the third option. Dumbledore's eyes moved around, he was watching Voldemort. It just seemed unlikely that Harry would be there by accident. Too many coincidences. Dumbledore's surprise seemed genuine. How had Harry snuck up on him? And Voldemort?

Draco remembered Hermione, appearing out of nowhere in the battle just outside this door.

Draco wanted to believe that Harry was a hostage. It wasn't far fetched. Draco may have discovered Quirrell's secret, but Dumbledore had said "All of Tom Riddle's Icy Brilliance..." Tom Riddle must be Voldemort's real name. On some level Voldemort was Evil Harry. Or, perhaps, Harry was Good Voldemort.

That was a disturbing thought. Draco shuddered at the implications.

Voldemort only pretended to fly into a rage? Father had described scenes of Voldemort with Death Eaters (as second hand descriptions). Voldemort didn't appear sane. But if Voldemort was Quirrell, that meant he already knew the lessons Quirrell taught. How to Lose. Martial Arts. A Voldemort that laughed at Harry's ridiculous ways to murder people as useless, because he had hundreds of non ridiculous ways.

A Voldemort so confident that he worked under the nose of his greatest enemy for a year - while dying and injured and far from the full height of his powers - just to teach and connect with his younger self. Or for some other reason, but viewing that as a benefit.

Quirrell was so cunning that he'd managed to fulfill multiple wishes with a single plot, just because he wanted to.

Draco thought, and the examples kept piling up. That was Voldemort? Not the bedtime monster Father described, but someone so cunning that Hogwarts itself - and everyone in it - was just an amusing plaything?

Draco remembered imagining Harry Potter as evil, trying to find a sign or clue, all the times he'd looked for a mistake. Now, at least, he had the cold comfort that he wasn't just deficient in imagination.

If this was true.

Why do I believe what I believe?

Then Draco thought about it again. Voldemort had defeated Dumbledore ... somehow. Dumbledore was gone, and this didn't seem like a ruse. If Quirrell was Voldemort and had Harry as a hostage, then he'd gotten the upper hand. That didn't make sense at all, that felt confusing. Draco got up and started pacing, when he came to the backside of the portal he saw that it had some thickness, but not nearly enough to hold the room Dumbledore was in. Draco read the words, and felt like he understood them, but when he looked away he couldn't remember what they meant. He want back around to the front, and looked through the portal. Draco put his hand out to see if he could touch it, but it felt like a sheet of glass, smooth and cool.

Draco considered the timeline. Dumbledore is waiting for Voldemort in this device, a doorway into another place. Presumably he knew Voldemort needed it. Dumbledore surprised Voldemort, but learned that Voldemort was possessing Quirrel. Voldemort traps Dumbeldore without any spell, so presumably he'd expected an ambush, and maybe brought Harry Potter along.

And then Harry Potter defeats Voldemort? No. On their best day the entire first year army would stand no chance against Professor Quirrell, unless they ambushed them. A clever Voldemort with enough time to plan to defeat Dumbledore. Draco could convince himself that Harry and Quirrell could defeat Voldemort, but Harry by himself AND facing Voldemort as smart as Quirrell? Was that really more likely than Voldemort had simply quit possessing Quirrell

That Voldemort had pretended to lose. He could be possessing anyone. He could be possessing Harry. Or they could be working together, for some purpose.

Despair washed over Draco. "This isn't an answer," he mumbled to the room, empty except for the shade of his former Headmaster. Then he shouted "I still don't know!" at the image of Albus Dumbledore, who was saying 'Hello, Tom' again. "It's not enough! How does this qualify as an answer? You trusted Harry knowing he was Voldemort, but Voldemort fooled you too!" Draco took out his wand and lashed out, cutting the portal, smashing spell after spell at it, first normal spells he'd use in classes and on the battlefield, then the spells Father had told him to not reveal. Draco levitated a chair from across the room and flung it at the portal. The chair itself shattered from the impact, leaving no cracks on the glass.

After a few minutes, exhausted, he slumped back to the ground, mumbling. "It's not fair. That's not an answer."

Draco woke up with a start, sitting at his desk.

Chapter 31: The Date, Pt 3

"Will you be all right?" Hermione asked, as they stood at his open door. Draco's face shone in the moonlight. Light from Xare, flashes of orange, danced across his face and especially his hair. "I mean, with your mother?"

"We're family," Draco said. "I'll worry about it later." The words hung in the humid air and Hermione saw him hesitate, just for a second, before bowing and disappearing into Malfoy Manor.

Hermione heard her parents' discussion as she glided down the stairs for breakfast.

"He's a lovely young man," Mum said. "And It's not like she's going to stay our little girl forever, Leo."

Hermione smelled the slightly stale coffee. She couldn't not smell it, just like she couldn't not hear her parents, even though they were two rooms away. At Hogwarts there were so many noises that even though she heard them all, none of them really registered. At home the quiet amplified everything.

"What kind of boy sends a bouquet like this, after a first date?" Dad grumbled, then slurped some coffee. Hermione could smell the flowers before she walked into the kitchen, but when she walked in she stopped. The vase stood in the middle of the table, and had a red carnation entwined with a yellow rose sporting thorns that looked like they'd been sharpened on a whetstone. A pink amaryllis stood above them, and they were surrounded by a collection of lavender peonies. Two lillies, one hanging languidly to each side, guarded the ensemble.

She walked over, entranced, as Mum said "Good morning" and inhaled the complex aromas that hung over the room.

The card simply said To: H, From: D.

Hermione broke from her reverie to kiss her parents.

"So, what are your plans for today?" Leo asked, as Hermione poured herself a glass of orange juice.

"There's a book I absolutely have to read," she answered.

Chapter 32: Portkeys, Trains and Carriages, Pt 1

"Only those who can dream of great Crimes ever suspect anything more than petty theft." - Lucius Malfoy

When Draco crossed the threshold of Platform Nine and Three Quarters his charcoal suit smoothly flowed into a robe.

Nobody witnessed the change. Draco wasn't showing off but he'd studied feverishly and practiced all during the holidays and it amused Draco. He knew it was a childish thrill, being sharply dressed in the correct fashion on both sides of the barrier. That realization didn't diminish his joy one bit, he'd dropped his Transfiguration at the exact right time.

It hadn't been a free Transfiguration; those took too long to master and he couldn't get nearly the amount of details down. His freely transfigured suits looked like they'd been tailored by a bunch of drunken forest creatures. Grindelwald had tutted dismissively when Draco told him that they started with free Transfiguration at Hogwarts. They started first years with fixed Transfigurations at Durmstrang.

Grindelwald and Dumbledore had argued pedagogy over the years.

"Of course Free Transfiguration is better," Grindelwald had said, "but what good does that do you right now? And roughly half the students will never be good at it. Bah. Yes, each fixed transfiguration requires it's own word and wand motions, but these can be derived. Did they not tell you that at school? Such strange teachings methods, that do not help the less talented get along yet also do not let the most talented shine. Come, pick some items, we will research it."

It had taken several days, but Draco had learned to Transfigure his robes into his suit. It doesn't count as bragging if nobody else hears, and Draco smiled when he stepped onto the platform, robes flowing smoothly around him. He kept up a brisk pace while his trunk padded behind him, moving through the crowd easily, saying hello, waving. Neville was already on the platform, fumbling through his trunk looking for Trevor. Draco didn't see Augusta Longbottom around. She'd probably already left. Vincent and Gregory were in an animated discussion, and Draco smiled even further when he saw they wore the matching robes he'd given them. His smile froze when Padma Patil glared at him, why would she be mad?

Oh, she likes me. Draco realized that she'd been around Slytherin, but had often hung around him instead of making new friends. She even joined the group rescuing you from the bullies, Draco remembered. At the time he'd just marked it down as Padma hanging out with Harry Potter and trying to make friends with the powerful students her age. In hindsight it was easy to see, and remember the other times he'd seen her and just assumed she was being friendly.

Your training never taught me anything about this, Father. Draco thought.

Six Month younger you didn't notice this, Father replied, so exactly how would you explain this to ten year old Draco?

Draco knew many of the complex love triangles. He probably knew more about them than any Wizard his age (although obviously less than any Witch his age). But he'd never thought the knowledge would apply to him. Draco smiled to Padma and waved as though nothing was wrong. I can't stop being oblivious now and walked over to the newsstand to see what fresh lies the Quibbler spewed.

GIRL-WHO-REVIVED DUELS NARCISSA MALFOY

SACKS MALFOY MANOR,

DRACO MALFOY PREGNANT?

"It's like they aren't even trying anymore," Draco said, as he slapped down four knuts and grabbed a copy. "I guess pregnancy news sells in the red tops."

"It does seem to at that," the vendor agreed.

"So, Hermione Granger came to my house, attacked my mother and then burned Malfoy Manor to the ground."

"Pity that," said that vendor. "It had lovely Feng Shui."

Draco flipped a page, "Then kidnapped me to be her love slave."

"You could do a lot worse, as abductors go," said the vendor. Seeing Draco's look, he raised his hands in a gesture of surrender. "Usually it's the ugly ones that stoop to that."

"At least our child is going to be the chosen one who saves the world. Seriously, who reads this stuff?"

"I've no idea."

Draco shoved the Quibbler into his mokeskin pouch. He'd show it Hermione later. Maybe she'd actually burn them down. It was a pleasant thought, though of course she'd never do it.

If you actually date Padma Patil, she'd burn the Quibbler down for you, Father said. Draco ignored him.

Draco walked back to the train, stopping to interject himself into a crowd of older Slytherins.

"Jugson, Derrick, Lestrange," he said, nodding slightly. "I trust your holidays went well?"

"Not as good as yours, Malfoy," said Peregrine Derrick, smiling and laughing. Draco noticed that the others didn't join in.

"Silly rumours," Draco said, "It's my burden that witches find me attractive. Tell me, Derrick, how do you manage to keep them away so easily?" Now Ethan Jugson and Lesath Lestrange started laughing and Peregrine Derrick didn't storm off, but just smiled wanly. With MacNair expelled and the Hestia Carrow still recovering the balance of power had shifted. I need to deal with the stragglers, but maybe they'll just give up.…. Draco turned to Ethan. "How is your brother doing? Settling in after the move?"

"Yeah. He's excited, wrote several letters about it," said Ethan then, in response to the Peregrine's look, "Robert moved out to the Caymans. Took a portkey last week. Said he wanted to strike out and make his fortune and that he was tired of school."

"Aren't we all?" said Derrick.

Lestrange spoke up. "It's just the first day back. You can't be tired of it until ... February." Draco nodded, That's new. He hadn't heard Lestrange speak up in a group in a long time. Usually he just sulked in his room or wandered the halls, lurking. Nobody was really sure what Lesath did, apart from ducking bullies. Maybe he'd also had a better time of it, after Hermione and Harry's anti-bullying campaigns. It took a while to recover from trauma. Draco perked up at the thought. If Lesath can recover from years of torment in under a year, I should be fine any day now. Draco saw Hermione boarding the train and excused himself. Derrick made a little whip cracking noise and everyone laughed, including Draco.

After stowing his trunk and climbing on board, Draco found Hermione in a car with Parvati Patil, Lavender Brown and Hannah Abbot. Besides them was a copy of Septavia Magnusson's Flowers, Arrangements and Their Meanings lying face down on the seat. Obviously Hermione hadn't set it down, she wouldn't have left a book open like that, might damage the spine. Chocolate frog wrappers littered the floor. The witches' animated discussion stopped the instant Draco appeared. Draco blushed, then regained the use of his mouth.

"Hermione, I don't suppose you'd sack The Quibbler," Draco hoped his tone was light and playful. I must be insane, trying to talk to her when she's surrounded by her friends. Hermione shook her head and started to say something, but the other spoke up first.

"That's more of a third date sort of thing," Lavender Brown said.

"Good girls wait," agreed Hannah, nodding. There was giggling.

"Oh, I assure you Hermione was a perfect Lady and kept her hands to herself, but it never hurts to ask." Draco said to the assorted sniggers as Hermione blushed and stuttered. Insane or not, I can play that game. "Are you coming to Professor Slughorn's car?" Draco didn't bother to address the others, and tried to ignore their comments.

"No...I hadn't planned to. In any case I thought that wasn't until lunch?"

"My invite said eleven," Draco said. The Hogwarts Express let out a piercing whistle – last call – and Draco looked at his watch.

"You'd better get going, then," said Parvati.

"Yes, I suppose I should." Draco picked up the book and examined the page, then started reading out load. "Amaryllis – am I saying that right? – have a wide range of meanings with shades of subtleties. That is a nice turn of phrase, isn't it?" Draco thumbed through several more pages. "Fascinating book. You know, I really should read it some day." He leaned over to Hermione to hand the book back to her, winking when he hoped that the others couldn't see him. Then stood up, and made a small bow to the entire carriage.

"Ladies," he said, as he took his leave, shutting the door behind him.

That ought to keep them talking. Perhaps he should have made it seem like he was trying to hide the wink, but let them see. It probably didn't matter, and it's not like I can predict which would be better. Draco realized he'd have to seriously examine how his date with Hermione affected his reputation. And make sure that Hermione didn't misinterpret his joking. It certainly made things interesting. A number of students that Draco barely knew where talking about him, or at least whispering and pointing, as he made his way to the Professor's car. Then again, everyone always thinks that everything is about them. I'm probably just noticing the people who appear interested.

He passed Vincent and Gregory, sitting with Neville. Gregory waved him in, but Draco just flashed the invitation he'd been examining, shrugged, and kept walking. It definitely said 'Eleven am.' What would Professor Slughorn want to talk about in private? It could be the fallout from the expulsions, and the general course of House Slytherin. In his gut, Draco didn't believe that for a second. He slowed his pace, taking more time to say hello to people. No need to be early.

"Come in!" said Professor Slughorn to the knock. The Hogwart's Express lurched forward right as the door opened and Draco Malfoy stumbled slightly upon entering. There was a wide table between them and Draco's eyes scanned the settings, taking in the scene of (empty) chairs and eight elegant place settings. The glasses wobbled slightly as the train accelerated in small bursts, chugging forward. The table wasn't circular - no false equality here – and Horace sat at one end, able to view the entire table as well as the entrance to his private carriage.

"Draco, my boy! Take a seat, please. Would you like some tea?" Professor Slughorn didn't gesture towards any one particular seat, his hands were holding up a small pot of tea and he started to pour a second cup. He wanted to see where Draco chose to sit.

"Please. I wouldn't want you to have to reach across the table," Draco said, sitting down at the opposite end, He took out his wand and cast Wingardium Leviosa and gently drifted his tea to him and took a sip. "Fortunately, now that we're officially back at school, I don't have to inconvenience you."

Horace chuckled. "Oh, very good. But don't you want to sit at my right hand? You should want to impress your Professor and Head of House with your close rapport and set yourself up as my proxy over your fellow students."

"There will be students from all houses attending this, as I recall. And it is not clear to me that I want to be associated closely with my house. The opposite end of the table puts me in a similar position of authority, but as a counterbalance to yourself. Students naturally feel a pull to ally against Professors. And by sitting with my back to the door, I show implicit trust that I am safe from attack."

"Because of my presence? Or because of past events, I wonder? Well, either one works. And what of the non-Slytherins? What will they think?"

"They won't consciously notice the seating position in any case." Draco put down his tea, liquid still sloshing around. Professor Slughorn chuckled approvingly.

"Very good. Very good. I shouldn't test your training, but you mustn't blame an old man's curiosity. In any case, I don't even think most Slytherin pay much attention to these signals anymore. It's out of fashion. Did you not care for the tea? I have a wide variety to choose from. Darjeeling, perhaps?"

Draco's cup silently drifted back over to Professor Slughorn, who produced another pot of tea and poured into Draco's now-empty cup. Professor Slughorn refilled his own cup and took a nosy gulp before levitating Draco's tea back to him. He could see out of the corner of his eye that the significance wasn't lost on the boy. Draco quickly picked up his cup and took a sip.

"I honestly don't have much appreciation for the various types of tea. They taste mostly identical. If you hadn't said it was Darjeeling, I wouldn't have known." Draco set the cup back down.

Horace got up and went over to the trunk resting besides his chair, then opened it up and leaned dangerously far in, disappearing at the waist. "Next time I will stock some butterbeer, then? I may have something else ..." his voice disappeared for a few seconds, and the sound of rattling glass could be heard. "Hm. Perhaps I shouldn't offer underage students a wine - no matter how exquisite - while I am their official guardian and chaperone? What would the Headmistress say?"

Professor Slughorn stood up from his trunk and walked over to Draco, then offered him a small red and white can of Coke. "Or perhaps this is more to your taste?" Professor Slughorn gestured and Draco's cup turned into a tall glass, and he popped the can open and poured.

"Thank you, Professor. My unsubtle taste buds thank you as well. No point in asking how you knew about this," Draco said, picking up his glass and taking a drink of the still-fizzing soda.

Professor Slughorn sat down to Draco's left and he said "Tell me, my boy. What did you do this break? And where the hell is Gellart Grindelwald?" right as he met Draco's eyes.